<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Tvvo soveraigne salves for the soules sicknesse deliuered in certaine sermons at Hurst-church in the county of Berkes, neere Reading. By Robert Lovell, then minister and preacher of Gods word in the same parish.</title>
            <author>Lovell, Robert, curate of Allhallows, Barking.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 117 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06388</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16859</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102843</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838605</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838605</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2990</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06388)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2990)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1145:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Tvvo soveraigne salves for the soules sicknesse deliuered in certaine sermons at Hurst-church in the county of Berkes, neere Reading. By Robert Lovell, then minister and preacher of Gods word in the same parish.</title>
                  <author>Lovell, Robert, curate of Allhallows, Barking.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. S[nodham] for Nathanael Newbery, and are to be sould at the signe of the starre vnder St. Peters Church in Cornehill, and in Popes-head Ally,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2990:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2990:1"/>
            <p>TVVO SOVERAIGNE SALVES FOR THE <hi>SOVLES Sickneſſe: Deliuered Jn</hi> CERTAINE SERMONS at Hurſt-Church in the COVNTY of Berkes, neere READING. BY ROBERT LOVELL, then <hi>Miniſter</hi> and <hi>Preacher of Gods word in the ſame Pariſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROMANES 6.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Let not Sinne Raigne in your mortall bodies.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROVERBS. 22.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>They that Sowe vnto Iniquitie, ſhall Reape Affliction.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Peccatum eſt Fons et Mali, et Morbs, et Mortis.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Aretius in Iohn 5.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Ex ſanitate Animae fit ſanitas Corporis.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ariſt. Metaphiſic. lib. 7.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Newbery,</hi> and are to be ſould at the ſigne of the Starre vnder S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in Cornehill, and in Popes-head Ally. 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2990:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2990:2"/>
            <head>TO MY MVCH REVERENCED AND TRVELY RESPECTED Friend, Maſter ISAACH HORNE, <hi>Paſtor</hi> and <hi>Preacher</hi> of Gods ſacred Word at ELLSFIELD in <hi>Hampeſhire,</hi> To him Grace and Peace be Multiplyed.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>REVEREND SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S J was in the midſt of this Preaching-buſineſſe, it fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that a Letter of yours long ſince written vnto mee, came to my hands, wherein I perceiued your deſire of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomewhat on this enſuing Text. And I ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed much that it came no ſooner, that I might haue ſatisfied your deſire, and ſhewed my duty to him to whom I owe my ſelfe in ſo great a meaſure as I cannot expreſſe: for when mine owne father
<pb facs="tcp:2990:3"/>forſooke me, who tooke me in? When he receiued me againe to fauour, who reconciled vs? When he would haue bound me to a Trade; who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded him? When he would not heare of my go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Vniuerſitie;</hi> who preuailed with him but you? ſo that to ſpeake the truth,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tu Herus, Tu Patronus, Tu Pater eſſes.</hi> Yea, without Exceſſe of ſpeech, or Suſpition of flattery,<note place="margin">Plutarch. de vita Alex.</note> I may truely ſay of you as <hi>Alexander</hi> did of <hi>Ariſtotle; Hic mihi Principium vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uendi dedit, Iſte autem Bene viuendi ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem tradidit.</hi> For who in the Countrey gaue me either Countenance or Maintenauce in my courſe of Schollerſhip, but you? I ſpeake <hi>Truely,</hi> I bleſſe God <hi>Humbly,</hi> I thanke you <hi>Heartily,</hi> It was <hi>You,</hi> and none but <hi>You</hi> that did it. But <hi>Quid re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribuam?</hi> Like for Like? I cannot, for your <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours</hi> are beyond my <hi>Deſerts,</hi> and your <hi>Deſerts</hi> are aboue the reach of my <hi>Requitall. Siluer</hi> and <hi>Gold</hi> haue I none, but ſuch as I haue, giue I vnto you; to wit, <hi>Duty</hi> for <hi>Loue; Loue and Reſpect</hi> for <hi>your louing me when I was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Loued nor Reſpected.</hi> In token of which I ſend theſe vnpoliſhed papers, but how? not to <hi>Direct</hi> you, but that you ſhould <hi>Correct</hi> them.</p>
            <p>My <hi>Schoole-exerciſes</hi> haue beene oft cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected
<pb facs="tcp:2990:3"/>by you, and now I refuſe not that my <hi>Church-ſeruices</hi> be cenſured with your <hi>Delea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur</hi> For I am of that Fathers minde, which in all his workes and writings did not onely deſire <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Lectorem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. proae. ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Lib. 3. de Trinitae.</note> 
               <hi>fed etiam Liberum Correcto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi> I therefore chooſe that I might be <hi>Blamed</hi> of you by your <hi>friendly ſmitings,</hi> rather then <hi>Balmed</hi> of Carping <hi>Momus,</hi> and Scourging <hi>Zoilus,</hi> with their <hi>Precious</hi> (or rather <hi>Pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi>) <hi>Balmes,</hi> which euer yet were found of the <hi>Ingenious,</hi> nay <hi>Religious,</hi> to be rather <hi>Hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> then <hi>Helpefull</hi> to their <hi>Heads</hi> and <hi>Hearts.</hi> And further I craue that if you meete with any, <hi>Qui vel non Intelligendo Reprehendunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. contra Fauſtam. lib. 22. cap. 34.</note> 
               <hi>vel Reprehendendo non intelligunt,</hi> that you would be as ſilent with ſuch as may be: ſay little to them, and leſſe of them, leſt in your prayers, you will beg with me, <hi>That they might be either of a more ſound Iudgement, or ſober and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified Affection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confeſſe it to be a ſhrew'd aduenture to traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique with one poore talent in <hi>Publique,</hi> whilest I behold richer graces buried in <hi>Silence.</hi> But iudging it better to Husband a <hi>Little</hi> to the Common good, rather then to hoard vp <hi>Much in Sullen Niggardize,</hi> I ſend it into the world. It
<pb facs="tcp:2990:4"/>is but a yong plant, yet yong plants thriue, if the Sunne warme them with it's beames. Caſt then your eye of acceptance on theſe <hi>weake</hi> beginnings and you ſhall hearten mee in my proceedings. Which hoping, I commend againe to your kind ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, and your ſelfe with it, to the bleſsing of our gracious God, and doe reſt with all due reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Study at Saint</hi> Michaels <hi>in</hi> Crooked Lane, <hi>Lond.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>25. of</hi> Nou. <hi>1620.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your poore Scholler in all Chriſtian ſeruices to be commanded, <hi>ROBERT LOVELL.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2990:4"/>
            <head>To the Courteous <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas the common excuſe for the <hi>Preſſe</hi> is <hi>Ouer-preſsing Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity;</hi> I will not preſſe thee to beleeue that of me, but I will ingenuouſly acknowledge that my ſpeciall apologie for my preſumption in this kinde is <hi>Opportunity,</hi> leſt I might ſeeme vnthankefull vnto him to whom I ſo much owe my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Looke thou on the <hi>Thing</hi> without regarding the <hi>Perſon,</hi> on the <hi>Matter</hi> without reſpecting the <hi>Man,</hi> and I doubt not but that it may profit thee. Which if it doth;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Homeroma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtix</hi> was <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> Scourge, of whom all Railers and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious Carpers are called <hi>Zoili. Plutarch.</hi>
               </note> pleaſure me then but ſo much as to ſhield mee what thou may'ſt from that <hi>Zoilus</hi> or <hi>Homero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſtix</hi> whom I know will rather <hi>Except</hi> againſt it, then <hi>Accept</hi> of it. Yet I muſt tell thee truely, that I ſuſpect not the biting of any Curre, but the Cubbe of that Foxe which doth diſpraiſe the Grapes which he cannot reach: For no ſuch enemy to <hi>Art</hi> as <hi>Idi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2990:5"/>
            <p>But if thou, who art Iudicious, doſt hap to finde ought in it which is worthy of <hi>Reproofe; Blame</hi> mee then, but <hi>Blaſe</hi> me not, <hi>That is Charitie;</hi> or if thou findeſt ought in it worthy of <hi>Prayſe, Bleſſe</hi> him that made me the Inſtrument of his glory heerein; <hi>That is Pietie.</hi> And thus doing, thou ſhalt ſurely ſet me with cheerefulneſſe to a further benefitting of Gods Church, which that I may I craue thy prayers for mee, and aſſure thee of mine for thee, and ſo I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my Study at Saint <hi>Michaels</hi> in <hi>Crooked Lane,</hi> Lond. <date>25. of <hi>Nou.</hi> 1620.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Thy ſeruant in Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>ROBERT LOVELL.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="doctrines">
            <pb facs="tcp:2990:5"/>
            <head>The Doctrines, with other ſpeciall <hi>notes herein contained.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>1</label> That Gods workes, whether of Mercy or Iugdement, whether on our ſelues or others, ought not to be ſleigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but to be marked, to be noted, yea duely and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be conſidered off. <hi>Pag. 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>2</label> That though ſinne hath Reſidency in vs, yet it ought not to Raigne in vs. <hi>Pag. 6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The meanes to haue victory ouer ſinne. <hi>Pag. 9.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The runges by which Sinne gets into its Throne. <hi>Pag. 12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>3</label> That ſickneſſe For ſinne doth follow ſickneſſe In ſin. <hi>Pag. 14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>4</label> That our deliuerance from any yoke or bondage of ſinne, or ſinnes Conſequence, (which is Sickeneſſe, or Miſery, or Trouble) ſhould be a ſtrong bond to binde vs to the ſeruice of God. <hi>Pag. 21.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>5</label> That when God doth worke any thing In, Vpon, or By vs, we ought not to attribute the vertue and power of it to our ſelues, but vnto God. <hi>Pag. 22.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>6</label> That Puniſhment ſhall certainly follow ſinne. <hi>Pag. 27.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Wherein is noted the difference of Gods puniſhing the godly and the wicked. <hi>Pag. 28.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>7</label> That God will bring greater and heauie plagues on men, when they will not profit by leſſer. <hi>Pag. 31.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2990:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2990:6"/>
            <head>TWO <hi>SOVERAIGNE SALVES</hi> For the SOVLES SICKENESSE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IOHN 5.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Behold, thou art made whole, Sinne no more: leſt a worſe thing come vnto thee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the faithfull Phyſitian of the body,<note place="margin">Chemniſius Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. cuang. lib. <hi>2.</hi> pag. <hi>160.</hi> in <hi>4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> hauing cured his Patient, if at any time after he can meete with him, will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh him to take heede of ſuch dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et as may hurt him, for feare of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe, (which commonly proues worſe then the former diſeaſe:) So Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, that good Phyſitian of the ſoule, meeting in the <hi>Temple,</hi> the man which he had healed of a <hi>long and loathſome diſeaſe,</hi> doth admoniſh him to be more carefull in time to come then formerly he had beene, for feare <hi>Leſt a worſething, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as Chriſt then met with <hi>That man in his perſon:</hi> ſo doth he now meete with vs in his <hi>Word;</hi> Therein ſhewing vs, 1. <hi>Our miſerie.</hi> 2. <hi>His mercie. Our miſerie,</hi> in that we are <hi>ſicke</hi> in <hi>body, ſicke</hi> in <hi>ſoule,</hi> and <hi>ſinfull</hi> in both. His <hi>mercis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ne quod per gratiam accepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus peccando a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note> in that being thus <hi>ſicke,</hi> thus <hi>ſinfull,</hi> he doth notwithſtanding vouchſafe to <hi>heale vs,</hi> and <hi>healing vs</hi> doth admoniſh vs alſo to take heed <hi>That wee ſinne no more, leſt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:2990:7"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Senſus verbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vior.</note>The words for plainneſſe ſake may be thus explained: <hi>Thou art whole,</hi> that is. <hi>Though through ſinne thou waſt ſicke, by reaſon of wickedneſſe thou waſt weake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thou art whole.</note> 
               <hi>by meanes of thine iniquities thou couldſt not looke vp, much leſſe leape into the poole of Betheſda and now thou art</hi> MADE <hi>whole,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Made whole.</note> 
               <hi>not of thine owne merit, nor by the ſtrength of thine owne power,</hi> Therefore</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sin no more.</note> 
               <hi>Sinne no more,</hi> that is, <hi>Draw no more ſo oft of it, Drinke no more ſo deepe of it. Ruſh no more ſo violently into it, Walke no more ſo inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinately in it. Wallow not any more ſo filthily in it, Let Sathan no more triumph ouer thee by opp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ting and enthralling thy ſoule, Let ſinne no more lead thee without orpoſition and manly reſiſtance, Let it not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more raigne in thee, Obey not the luſts of it, Giue not thy members any more as weapons to ſight for it, but oppoſe it, reſiſt it, and manfully fight againſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Leſt a worſe thing come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee.</note> 
               <hi>Leſt a worſe thing come vnto thee,</hi> that is, <hi>Some thing worſe then that. Firſt, a worſe dammage to thy bodie, or which is worſe then it, perhaps damnation to thy ſoule. Leſt continuing obſtinate thou bee of the number of them that are numbred to the ſword, that be bowed downe to the ſlaughter, that cry, and be not anſwered, that ſpeake and be not leard, for if thou art; My father wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> whet h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> glittering ſword, and ſharpen his poyſoned arrowes, with the one whereof he will eate thy fleſh, and with the other drinke vp thy blood, take hold of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and executing vengeance, yea, and wounding thy hairy ſcalpe, if thou goe on in thy wickedneſſe.</hi> Therefore <hi>Breake vp thy fallow ground, Sow no more among thorres, be circumciſed vnto the Lord, and be no more ſtiffe-necked.</hi> Yea, <hi>ſinne thus no more, leſt. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words now in a more orderly handling,<note place="margin">Diuiſio.</note> doe without ruſhing fall aſunder into two parts,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> to wit.
<list>
                  <item>1. An admonition or iniunction.</item>
                  <item>2. The Reaſons therof.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The iniunction is, <hi>Sin no more.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> The Reaſons are drawne.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. <hi>A priore, á Fronte,</hi> or, <hi>á conſideratione collacati beneficy,</hi> from a benefit receiued. <hi>Thou art made whole</hi> The other reaſon is drawne; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>A Poſteriore, á Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> or, <hi>Terribili comminatione</hi> From an heauy threat of Gods vengeance, which is, <hi>Leſt a worſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here me thinkes I miſſe a word, not yet ſpoken off in my diuiſion, which becauſe it ſtands as a Porter at the gate, or as an Vſher to prepare for my enſuing diſcourſe; I cannot let it paſſe vnſaluted:<note place="margin">Behold.</note> the word is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Ecce, Behold.</hi> A word me
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2990:7"/>thinkes reſembling that <hi>Chaine</hi> which Poets faine to be <hi>tyed to the tongue of Mercury, and faſtened to the eares of the people,</hi> which <hi>Drew his Auditors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a <hi>Preparatiue</hi> word, a <hi>Peaceable</hi> word, a word of <hi>Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Zachar. 3.8.</note> a word of <hi>Admiration,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iſay 7.14.</note> a word of <hi>Attention,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 133.1.</note> a word of <hi>Precation,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Iohn 1.38.</note> a word of <hi>Exultation</hi> &amp; <hi>Expectation,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Iohn 1.29.</note> a word vſed in matters of <hi>Wonder,</hi> either of wonderfull <hi>Gladneſſe,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Luke 2.10.</note> or wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Sadneſſe</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Luke 1.20.</note>. It hath euer beene the <hi>Porter</hi> opening to, or the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> preparing for, matter of great moment and importance; as may be ſeene in theſe places. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 134.1. <hi>Luke</hi> 19.8. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.29. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.22.</p>
            <p>And I find it to haue a double office; the firſt <hi>Outward,</hi> the ſecond <hi>Inward.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Outwardly</hi> to prepare the eares, which be the firſt gates, by which Chriſt enters in to come at the heart.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Inwardly</hi> to prepare.
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>The Vnderſtanding.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>The Will.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Vnderſtanding</hi> to <hi>know,</hi> the <hi>Will,</hi> to <hi>acknowledge and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it ſelfe vnto that which is worthy to be beheld.</hi> And ſuch a <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi> is this; for <hi>Behold, a man was ſicke</hi> 38. <hi>yeares. Verſ.</hi> 5. Yea,<note place="margin">Verſe 5.</note> 
               <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi> him ſo ſicke as that he was not <hi>able at the ſtirring of the Poole, to ſteppe in as ſoone as others. ver.</hi> 7. Yet <hi>Behold,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
               <hi>this man at one word of Chriſts; He aroſe, tooke vp his bed and walked, Verſe</hi> 8.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> yea, and as my Text ſaith, he <hi>was made whole.</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> A worke worth the wondering at, a worke well deſeruing to be vſhered with an <hi>Ecce,</hi> for who would but diligently marke, who could but both aſpectiuely and inſpectiuely <hi>Behold</hi> ſuch a thing as this? yea, looke on it not a ſquint or glauncingly, but with both eyes, to view it; yea, to view it with the eyes of the body, and to note it with the eyes of the minde; All which is all one with the word <hi>Conſider</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">1 Sam. 12.24 Pſal. 50 22.</note> to which the <hi>Holy Chriſt</hi> powerfully addeth another word, which is <hi>See, Behold and See</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">I Lam. 1 12.</note>, as if hee had ſaid, <hi>Intenta animi cogitatione,</hi> ſaith <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Auguſt</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Auga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; Litera. cap. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note>. <hi>Looke well vpon it, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it with an inward, eager, earneſt, &amp; ſerious conſideration</hi> Which word, what can it in this place more naturally affoord, then this? <hi>That Gods workes, whether of Mercyor Iudgement,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>whether on our ſelues or others, ought not to be Sleighted but to be Marked, to be Noted, yea, duely and diligently to be conſidered off.</hi> Which point, becauſe it ariſeth but from one word, we wil end it with two or three at the vtmoſt, and then come to the other words of my Text.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:2990:8"/>
            <p>We ſee it daily betweene man and man, that the not min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a good turne, the ſlackneſſe in acknowledging thereof, and the not endeuouring to requite it, makes the giuer cold in continuance of his former fauours: how much more ſhall God doe likewiſe? If he daily powre out his benefits vpon vs, if he continually healeth our ſickeneſſe, yea, and mercifully for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueth our ſinnes, and yet we will not <hi>Behold conſider and attend it,</hi> what hope is there of continuance of them? ſurely little or none: For God cannot endure that his bleſſings be ſwallowed in the graue and gulfe of forgetfulneſſe, but the more we haue from him, the more he craues from vs, Vnto which if his benefits bind vs not, if his mercies allure vs not, if the cords of his loue draw vs not, hee will ceaſe <hi>beholding vs,</hi> hee will no more <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider our miſeries,</hi> nor <hi>attend our cryes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee muſt therefore haue both our <hi>eares</hi> of <hi>attention,</hi> and <hi>hearts</hi> of <hi>retention,</hi> to <hi>heare, conſider, ponder and meditate</hi> on his mercies; <hi>Filling our mouthes with his praiſe; ſounding out his honour and glory all the day long,</hi> as well in <hi>Exultation for him,</hi> as he hath done in <hi>Exaltation of vs.</hi> So did <hi>Dauid</hi> euen prouoke all the people to heare what God had done for him; <hi>Come</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and hearken all ye people that feare God, and I will tell you what hee hath done for my ſoule</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 66.5.16.</note>. Againe, when the Shepheards had found the words of the Angell true, and ſeene the Babe laid in the cratch, they <hi>hid</hi> it not, they kept it not <hi>ſecret,</hi> but <hi>they publiſhed it</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Luke 2.17.</note> ſaith the Text: and ſo muſt we doe likewiſe, and that both in reſpect of <hi>God, our ſelues, and others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>1</label> in reſpect of <hi>God,</hi> whoſe glory, praiſe and honour, is much ſet forth thereby.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, in regard of <hi>our ſelues,</hi> who thereby ſhall notably declare our faith. That we beleeue the works of God. <hi>I beleeued</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>and therefore did I ſpeake</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 116.10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nam vbi cun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eſt vera fides, ibi lingua ſonat confeſſionem propter gloriam Dei &amp; ſalutem occleſiae</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Strigelius in Loc.</note>; For, whereſoeuer true faith is, there the tongue cannot be but as a trumpet to ſound out a ſound confeſſion, to the glory of God &amp; ſaluation of his choſen. Thirdly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> we muſt doe it for our <hi>brethren and companions ſakes. Peter being conuerted muſt ſtrengthen his brethren</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Luke 22.32.</note>: and we being partakers either of mercy or iudgement, of righteouſnes or peace, muſt not <hi>ſlight</hi> it, but marke, <hi>Behold, obſerue, and attend to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2990:8"/>it,</hi> as being a thing whereby God may be honoured, our ſelues comforted, and others edified.</p>
            <p>Which being ſo, let this inſtruct Parents of Children,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> and Maſters of Families <hi>to regiſter and record Gods works of iudgement; and meruaslouſneſſe in mercy, either towards themſelues or others:</hi> that ſo yee may be able out of your good treaſure of the one and other, to comfort and incourage them in goodneſſe, or to fright and feare them in committing euill. Fathers,<note place="margin">1 Paren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Behold and attend you the loue</hi> that God had to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his <hi>Seede,</hi> to <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and his <hi>Houſe,</hi> to <hi>Heſter</hi> and her <hi>Maides,</hi> becauſe the one did command <hi>his Sonnes,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Gen. 18.19.</note> the other <hi>his Houſhold,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Ioſh. 24.15.</note> the third <hi>her Maides,</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſter 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>To ſerue the Lord, to heepe his lawes. To faſt.</hi> And learne you by this to draw concluſions either of inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, imitation, or conſolation to your ſelue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and them. Againe, you Maſters of Families,<note place="margin">2 Maſters.</note> 
               <hi>Behold and attend you the iudgements of God on the wicked. His perfect hatred</hi> againſt <hi>Balthaſar</hi> for <hi>drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe,</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Dan. 5.25.</note> againſt <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cosby</hi> for <hi>Adultery,</hi>
               <note n="v" place="margin">Num. 25, 8.</note> againſt <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> for <hi>lying</hi> and <hi>diſſembling</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Acts 5.5.</note> and by ſuch exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples terrifie your beaſtlie Drunkards, affright your filthy Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers, diſmay your accuſtomed Lyers, that ſo no ſuch euils may happen to you and yours, as haue done to them and theirs; but being <hi>yet whole, Behold, haue a care, heed to it, that ye ſinne no more, leſt a worſe thing come vnto you.</hi> And ſo I paſte from this word of <hi>Admiration,</hi> to our Sauiours <hi>Iniunction</hi> which is, <hi>Sinne no more.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pars prima.</hi> Sinne no more.</note>
            </p>
            <p>What? <hi>ſinne no more?</hi> Will Chriſt haue this man a <hi>Catheran,</hi> a <hi>Celeſtine,</hi> a <hi>Donatiſt,</hi> a <hi>Perfectiſt?</hi> Will he haue <hi>abſolute obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the whole law?</hi> Or, <hi>totall immunitie from all ſinne?</hi> No, we leaue ſuch opinions to blinde heathen, to <hi>Pithagoras,</hi> and <hi>Zeno,</hi> who held <hi>that no ſtring or roote of vices at all, may be remaining in men through the exerciſe of vertue</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Jeromad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mad c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ponum.</note> or wee referre them to ſeduced Heretickes, olde <hi>Nouatus</hi> and <hi>Pelagius.</hi> (or to new-found <hi>Petrus Bruſius,</hi> a Frenchman, of the Prouince of Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone and <hi>Henricus</hi> his Scholler,) who in <hi>Augutines</hi> time helo <hi>that iuſt men may poſſibly fulfill the Law; and that the workes of holy men are abſolutely iuſt</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Aug. l. Hare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Har. <hi>38.</hi> et <hi>88.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> de bona ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> lib <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note>. And in <hi>Bernards</hi> time (ſaith a Reuerend Biſhop,) maintained <hi>that it was not impoſſible for a iuſt man to be quite without ſinne in this life.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>of Exceter</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>lanca. Tom. 1 pag. <hi>125.</hi> Col. <hi>1.</hi> in fol.</note> No, wee doe not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2990:9"/>ſo vnderſtand it, for wee are taught of God; <hi>that if wee ſay wee haue no ſinne, wee deceiue our ſelues, and there is no truth in vs</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">1 Ioh. 1.8.</note>. And therefore Chriſt in bidding this man to <hi>ſinne no more; Non exigit ab omni peccato vt immunis, ſed comparatio ſit ſuperio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris vitae</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Caluin. in loc.</note>: doth not require him to be <hi>free</hi> from <hi>all ſinne,</hi> but he ſpeakes in compariſon of his former life, which Chriſt knew without doubt to be euill, and that in an high degree. So that this diſſwaſion I take to be as much as if Chriſt had ſaid in more words, thus. <hi>Thou haſt formerly obeyed ſinne, now withſtand it; Thou waſt wont to yeeld to it, now ſtriue againſt it; Thou formerly madeſt a Paſtime of it, now let it be a Burthen vnto thee; Thou waſt wont to Delight in it, now Lament it; Thou formerly diddeſt let it raigne in thee, ſuffering it to play Rex, and to eſtabliſh its ſoueraigntie; its Edicts, its Lawes, its publiſhed Proclamations exacted ſeruice from thee, but now raigne thou ouer it; quench it, ſubdue it, and ſo ſhalt thou be ſafe:</hi> Which being the meaning, I meane hence to inferre.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>That though Sinne hath Reſidencie in vs, yet it ſhould not Raigne ouer vs</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Tametſi pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum in nobis Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidet, tamen ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdum eſt vt ad exer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m eius regnum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. Calumus in <hi>Rom. 6.12.</hi> &amp; Augan Text. tract. <hi>41.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p>Such is the taint of <hi>Sinne,</hi> as that we haue it Hereditarie from our firſt Parents, being deriued vnto vs for <hi>Adams</hi> fact.
<list>
                  <item>1. By iuſt imputation.</item>
                  <item>2. For want of originall iuſtice in our genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
                  <item>3. Becauſe of the deprauation and corrupt diſpoſition of our natures.</item>
               </list> Yea, we haue it <hi>Dwelling</hi> in vs, forcibly croſſing the motions of the ſpirit, haleing and pulling vs vnto ſinne; but if we <hi>Dwell not in it, if we let it not raigne in our mortall bodies,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 6.12.</note> 
               <hi>Sponte exequendo quod Peccatum imperat</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Caluin. in loc.</note>, readily obeying whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſinne commandeth, wee neede not feare its <hi>Reſidencie. Per Baptiſmum enim tollitur, non vt Non ſit, ſed ne Imputetur</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Aug. de Nup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tijs. cap. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note>: For by Baptiſme it is taken away, but how? not <hi>So</hi> taken away as that it is not in them after Baptiſme, but <hi>So,</hi> as that it is not <hi>accounted vnto</hi> them as <hi>ſinne, to whom all ſinne</hi> is forgiuen. And there are good reaſons why Sinne ſhould not haue this dominion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Firſt, looke backe to our <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> in which being <hi>Baptiſed</hi> into <hi>Chriſt, we haue put on Chriſt</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Gal. 3.27.</note>. Proclaiming him to be our King, and vowing our ſelues to be his Subiects, and how can we then for feare or ſhame <hi>let ſinne raigne in vs?</hi> The Spirit ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>Deified vs by Baptiſme</hi> (ſaith <hi>Nazianzine</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Nazian. de bap. orat. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>) that is, by Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe made vs <hi>Partakers of the Godly nature,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.4.</note>;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2990:9"/>yea, being by <hi>It deliuered out of Priſon, diſcharged from the debt we owed, It hauing deliuered vs alſo from Death, regenerated the Soule, gorgeouſly arrayed it, and made paſſage for the Kingdome of heauen,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Baſil,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Baſil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ad P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>) how ſhall we then ſuffer ſinne to <hi>raigne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Secondly, ſee Sinne, who, or what it is; <hi>Sinne</hi> is a <hi>Tyrant</hi> yea ſuch a <hi>Tyrant</hi> as thruſteth himſelfe by force and fraud into our beſt hold<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, ſo to ſhoulder our the right owners; which who will (if he know him) entertaine in his houſe, much leſſe <hi>let raigne in his heart? Sinne</hi> indeed is a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> yea, a <hi>Conſuming, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting, Inſatiable, and Holding Tyrant.</hi> For being <hi>dead</hi> in it, <hi>we are holden</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 7.6. <hi>De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eneb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntur.</hi>
               </note>, that is, <hi>forcibly holden, Holden</hi> in a miſerable ſlauery and bondage, both of the power of the law, of the rigour of the law, and of the curſe of the law. <hi>Sinne</hi> like a <hi>Tyrant</hi> ouerturneth all lawes and conſtitutions, it maketh its owne will its law, which when we haue entertained and obeyed, and ſuffered to raigne, what ſlauery is like ours? Surely none. No, not <hi>the Iſraelites oppreſſion in Egypt,</hi> nor <hi>their vnmercifull entreatie in</hi> Babilon; not <hi>the bloudy perſecution of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus,</hi> nor <hi>the Turkes Gallie ſlauerie;</hi> not <hi>the Popes fire,</hi> nor <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts Gunpowder;</hi> not <hi>the Spaniards Inquiſition,</hi> nor <hi>Amſterdam Browniſts</hi> mercileſſenes are not to be compared vnto it. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member a pretty queſtion of the Orators, and it is this:<note place="margin">Cicero Tarad. <hi>5</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>An ille liber ſit, cui mulier imperat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cui leges imponat?</hi> Whether he be a free man, whom a woman may command, and vnto whoſe lawes he muſt be obedient? And he anſwereth: <hi>Iſtum non ſolum ſeruum, ſed nequiſſimum ſeruum;</hi> That ſuch an one is not onely a Seruant, but a Slaue, yea, an vnhappy bondſlaue; <hi>Etiamſian am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſſima familia natus ſit,</hi> though he be both borne and bred and brought vp in neuer ſo ample, neuer ſo honourable a familie. I ſpeake it not to approue the Orators ſpeech, I condem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e it rather, but it will ſerue to inferre that the ſame may be ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld of <hi>ſinne.</hi> For if any perſonall vice doth but obtaine its rege<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cie, what will it not make vs to doe? <hi>Poſcit, et dandum eſt; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ocat, et veniendum; Eijcit, et abcundum; Minatur, et extimeſcendum:</hi> It craues, and we muſt giue; it cals, and wee muſt come: it caſts vs out, and we muſt be gone; it threatens, and we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are. Nay, and if this were all it were well, but it is not; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by as <hi>ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny,</hi> it makes <hi>the fruit of the wombe,</hi> which is a <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> to be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2990:10"/>a <hi>Curſe,</hi> it makes <hi>God</hi> of a <hi>tender Father,</hi> to be a <hi>terrible Iudge;</hi> it makes <hi>Chriſt</hi> which is a <hi>corner-ſtone to ſupport,</hi> to be a <hi>ſtone of offence</hi> to <hi>ſlumble</hi> at; yea, it makes the <hi>Goſpell</hi> which is of it ſelfe <hi>glad tidings,</hi> to be vnto vs <hi>heauie newes, euen the ſauour of Death vnto Death:</hi> oh therefore let it not <hi>raigne in vs,</hi> but rather let vs deale with <hi>Sinne</hi> as with a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> and that on this wiſe. 1. <hi>Take away its weapons.</hi> 2. <hi>Baniſh its friends.</hi> 3. <hi>Preuent its pollicies.</hi> 4. <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer offer conditions of peace with it,</hi> for if we doe, it will quickly encroach and get the chayre of eſtate, and ſit in our ſoules as King. <hi>Therefore let it not Raigne, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>3</label> Laſtly, conſider <hi>ſins</hi> wages: when it hath made vs to take paines, what will be our pay? Surely in this life <hi>a galeing and wounded Conſcience,</hi> which ſhall continually ſuggeſt vnto vs <hi>our ſinnes committed, Gods law violated, his Maieſtie offended, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment deſerued.</hi> This <hi>Worme</hi> ſhall <hi>gnaw,</hi> this <hi>Scourge</hi> ſhall <hi>whip vs</hi> in this life.</p>
            <q>Occultum quatiente animo tortore flagellum.<note n="o" place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>menal. ſat. <hi>13</hi>
               </note>
            </q>
            <p>Yea, the Tormentor ſhall ſhake an hidden whippe in the ſoule of the Tormented. Nay, neither is this all, but <hi>Death</hi> ſhall alſo play its part, for <hi>That</hi> indeed is <hi>ſins proper pay,</hi> as the Apoſtle witneſſeth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. ſaying, <hi>The wages of ſinne is death. Mors vt debitum ſoluitur peccanti; vti Militi ſtipendium ſuum ex pacto</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Aretius in Rom. <hi>6.23.</hi>
               </note> Death is the Sinners due, and ſhall be as ſurely paid him, as the Souldier hath his preſſe money, and the Seruant his couenant penny. <hi>Therefore let not ſinne raigne, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My application of which point ſhall be none other but this:<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> namely, to inſtruct vs, <hi>Therefore to raigne ouer ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which if we will doe, we muſt as warlike-kings fight luſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and with a good courage, fearing none but God, and yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to nothing but godlineſſe, which hath <hi>the promiſe of this life and that which is to come:</hi> Both which if we will doe, wee muſt follow the counſell of the Apoſtle, who willeth vs, <hi>To take the whole armour of God, that wee may be able to withſtand the aſſaults of the Deuill,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Eph. 6.11.</note> and to <hi>Reſiſt in the euill day, and to ſtand faſt</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">v. 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Know this, oh thou Chriſtian man whatſoeuer thou art, that liuing here thou liueſt in a <hi>Millitary world</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">1 Cor. 7.31.</note> and in a <hi>Church Millitant</hi>
               <note n="v" place="margin">1 Tim. 2.15.</note>.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2990:10"/>
            <p>Thou muſt therefore be a <hi>Souldier,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.3.</note> and the courſe of thy life muſt be a <hi>fight</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.18.</note>, thou muſt expect the oppoſition of <hi>ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Luke 1.71.</note>, and annoyance with <hi>aſſaults</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.11.</note>: And therefore like a good <hi>Souldier</hi> thou muſt <hi>fight manfully,</hi> that thou maiſt <hi>raigne Regally.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before thou entreſt combat with thy foes, <hi>Put on thine armour,</hi> be euery way, &amp; in euery <hi>thing</hi> wel inſtructed, as M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin</hi> expounds it.<note n="a" place="margin">Quo ſigniſicat debere omni ex parte inſtructor eſſe ne quod no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis deſit.</note> But what <hi>Armour</hi> muſt thou <hi>put on? Not Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans Bow; nor Sampſons Iaw bone: not Dauids Sling; nor Peters Sword: not Shamgars Goade, nor Saules Speare:</hi> For <hi>wee wreſtle not againſt fleſh and bloud &amp;c.</hi> But <hi>againſt Principalities and powers, againſt worldly Gouernours, and Princes of the darkeneſſe of this world, againſt ſpirituall wickedneſſes, and things which are in high places</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Epheſ. 6.13.</note>. <hi>Eó ergo plus nobis eſt negoty &amp; moleſtia</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Calum in Loc</note>: And therefore ſo much the more buſineſſe and trouble. <hi>If</hi> then thou wilt be a Conquerour, follow that Captaines counſell that bids thee put on <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Vniuers;ain armaturam Dei: The Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of God.</hi> So called, becauſe it was <hi>made of God. I am.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Preſcribed by God. Pſal.</hi> 119 98. <hi>Giuen of God.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to God. Heb.</hi> 13.21. <hi>Made in heauen. Preſcribed in his Word. Giuen by his Spirit. Agreeable to his Will:</hi> Therefore <hi>the Armour of God.</hi> The peeces of which Armour are theſe.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>The Girdle of Veritie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The Breaſt-plate of Righteouſneſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>The Shoes of Peace.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4.<hi>The Shield of Faith.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>The Helmet of Hope.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6 <hi>The Sword of the Spirit</hi>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">Epheſ. 6.14.15.16.</note>.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, girt thee with the <hi>Girdle of Verity.</hi> Haue in thee,<note place="margin">1 The Girdle of Veritie.</note>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Truth of Iudgement;</hi> Whereby, through illumination of the Spirit, and information of the word of God,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> thou remayneſt ſetled and eſtabliſhed in that doctrine that it teacheth.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Truth of Heart,</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> whereby thou ſeekeſt to approue thy ſelfe before God, who (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>Loues truth in the inward affections</hi>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 51.6.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Haue in thee <hi>truth of ſpeech,</hi> wherby thy <hi>mouth</hi> and thy <hi>minde,</hi> thy <hi>heart</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and thy <hi>tongue,</hi> that are ſo cloſely tyed by natures bond, may not be vnknit, or vnlooſed by the Deuil, which is a <hi>lyer,</hi> but rather <hi>Speake thou the Truth vnto thy neighbour.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 Haue in thee, <hi>Truth of</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                     <hi>action,</hi> whereby thou approueſt thy ſelfe <hi>plaine, faithfull and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt</hi> in all thy dealings and doings both with God and Man, this done,</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:2990:11"/>
            <p>Then couer thy ſelfe with the <hi>Breaſt-plate of Righteouſneſſe;</hi> whereby the vitall parts of thy ſoule,<note place="margin">2 The Breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</note> to wit, <hi>A good conſcience, ſanctification, and a godly life,</hi> may be preſerued and kept from being mortally wounded, or downe-right killed. Thus coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſlacke not <hi>to ſhooe thy feete with the preparation of the Goſpell of Peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 The Shooes of Peace.</note> by which <hi>greaues and leg-harneſſe,</hi> being preſerued from the Bryars and Thornes, Stones and Stickes that are in thy way, that is, Afflictions and perſecutions, tentations and trialls in thy profeſſion and practiſe of Chriſtianity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thou mayeſt march valiantly, fight luſtily, and ouercome both quickely and comfortably. Thus <hi>Shod,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4 The Shield of Faith.</note>Thou muſt haue a great car, yea, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. A care <hi>aboue all things els,</hi> that thou <hi>ſhield thee with the ſhield of Faith;</hi> wherby thou maieſt keepe both thy <hi>Head and thy Heart,</hi> from the <hi>han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy-gripe, blowes and ſtripes, foyles and puſhes</hi> of thine <hi>own</hi> corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which are within thee as alſo <hi>Quench the fiery darts of the Deuill:</hi> Which hauing maliciouſly poyſoned, hee ſhootes at thee a farre off alſo, with which if thou art wounded, thou ſhalt be ſo inflamed, enraged, and in ſuch a burning paine, as that if <hi>the ſhield of faith quench it not, coole it not, aſſwage it not,</hi> by belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the promiſes of God, and applying the bloud of Chriſt to thy ſoule, it cannot be but that thou ſhouldeſt <hi>be vexed in thy Bones</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 6.2.</note>, <hi>ſore vexed in thy Soule</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Verſe 3.</note>, <hi>faint in thy mourning</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Verſe 6.</note>, <hi>and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with Griefe</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Iob 3.3. &amp;. 6.2.</note>; therefore ſpecially ſhield thee with <hi>That,</hi> for it is the chiefe <hi>Balme,</hi> and moſt medicinable <hi>Oyle</hi> of thy ſoule, which being applyed to that facultie which is enflamed with Sathans poyſoned dart, aſſwageth the heate, driueth out the poyſon, diſpelleth the inward anguiſh thereof, pacifieth and quieteth it, and ſo cureth the wounds thereof: Yea, and makes them ſo ſound, as that thou ſhalt be able at laſt to ſay with <hi>Iob, Yea though hee ſlay me, yet will I put my truſt in him</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Iob 13.15.</note>. But being thus <hi>ſhielded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">5 The Helmet of hope.</note>Thou muſt haue alſo <hi>the Helmet of Hope, or Saluation</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Salutaris. Cal. in loc.</note>, with which thy head, nay heart and ſoule being couered, kept and fenced, thou ſhalt not feare thine aduerſaries, but meete them in the Gappe, boldly confronting them, and manfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding them.</p>
            <p>Laſtly thou muſt not be without thy <hi>Sword girt vnto thy Thigh,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2990:11"/>with which <hi>liuely, powerfull, ſharpe, piercing, diuiding,</hi>
               <note place="margin">6 The Sword of the Spirit.</note> 
               <hi>diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Heb. 4.14.</note> weapon, thou ſhalt both defend thy ſelfe, and foyle thy foe; prouided alwayes, that thou haſt <hi>Knowledge and Wiſedome; Knowledge,</hi> to <hi>Vnderſtand</hi> what is Gods good will and pleaſure; and <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> to <hi>Apply</hi> it. And now becauſe without being armed with the <hi>Power of Gods might,</hi> thou art but like little <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> with <hi>Sanls Helmet of Braſſe, Brigandine and Sword.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.38. therefore I would aduiſe thee to take to thee, <hi>Prayer and all manner of Supplication in the Spirit</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Epheſ. 6.18.</note>, which will helpe thee well to weild and vſe thy aforenamed Armour: Which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus put on, thou needeſt not feare either <hi>Sinnes Dominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> or <hi>Damnation:</hi> For <hi>Sinne</hi> with it's Author the Deuill, is of that cowardly ſpirit, as that being <hi>Reſiſted it will flie</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Iam. 4.7.</note>. By which Flight, thou ſhal haue Freedome, both from his and it's Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall Regiment; no ſinne ſhall haue dominion ouer thee, but thou ſhalt as Lord and King haue dominion ouer it; yea, thou ſhalt <hi>Sinne no more (as hereto fore thou haſt ſinned.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet ſuch is the ſubtilty of ſinnes-Author the Deuill, that if we take not great heed, and continuall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re, it will by little and little ſteale into our hearts, and ſo inthronize it ſelfe into our ſoules, as that we ſhall not be able (without the fatherly and fauourable aſſiſtance of the Almighty to raigne ouer it. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I hold it wiſedome for euery Chriſtian, carefully to marke ſinnes foot-ſteps, whereby it climbeth into our hearts and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it's Throne in our Soules, (for, <hi>Nemo Repenté fit Peſſimus ſed Paulatim deſcendit</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Bern. de gradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Humilitat.</note>: No man is on the ſudden deſperately euill, but deſcendeth by little and little;) yea, <hi>Canker</hi>-like it creepeth by degrees, which the <hi>Pſalmograph</hi> maketh three in number, that is, <hi>Walking, Standing, Sitting</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">Pſal. 1.1.</note>, but the <hi>Ancients,</hi> foure, to wit,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Cogitatio.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Propofitum.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Actio.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duratio</hi>
                     <note n="t" place="margin">Iarob de valen. in Pſa. <hi>91.5, 6, 7</hi>
                     </note>:</item>
               </list> Thought, Purpoſe, Performance, and Continuance. By <hi>Thoughts,</hi> ſinne cauſeth vs to ſtumble; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> By <hi>Purpoſes</hi> it maketh vs to <hi>Fall;</hi> By <hi>Performance</hi> it cauſeth vs to <hi>Lye Proſtrate;</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> By <hi>Continuance</hi> it maketh vs <hi>Obdurate;</hi> Which is it's full pitch,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and tallest growth, yea, ſinnes <hi>Noone tyde,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> quia iam Poccator non ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met ſuam famam:</hi> For now the ſinner hath eaten ſhame,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> and drunke after it; and therefore that Sinne might haue both it's <hi>Reſidencie</hi> and <hi>Regencie,</hi> he will not ſticke to commit it.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Euery
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2990:12"/>whit.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Euery where.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>And euer;</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> or if you will.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>All.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>At all Places.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>At all Times</hi>
                     <note n="v" place="margin">Stonham in Pſal. <hi>1.1.</hi> pag. <hi>16.</hi> in <hi>4<hi rend="sup">to.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </note>.</item>
               </list> Theſe are the <hi>rungs,</hi> by which Sinne gets it's throne in our inner man; In which when it is a while eſtabliſhed, ſee how it proclaimeth it ſelfe <hi>King,</hi> and playes <hi>Rex.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. By <hi>Ignorance,</hi> which <hi>Blindeth;</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. By <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe,</hi> which <hi>Diſpleaſeth;</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. By <hi>Cuſtome,</hi> which <hi>Hardneth;</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. By <hi>Security,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Ignorance.</note> which <hi>Preſumeth.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> By <hi>Ignorance</hi> the <hi>Gentiles were Strangers to the Life of God</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.18.</note>, and the <hi>Romanes</hi> were <hi>deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> into a <hi>Reprobate minde</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 1.28.</note>; yea, this the Apoſtle doth put firſt in that Catalogue of cauſes: <hi>They Regarded not to Know God,</hi> ſaith he, and why? <hi>Sponte neſciunt, vt Liberius peccent,</hi> ſaith <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aquin</hi> 2 2 <hi>queſt.</hi> 76. <hi>art<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 4.</note>: They were wilfully ignorant, that they might ſinne the more freely; yea, and whence is it that our common people haue gotten ſuch boldneſſe in ſinning? is it not for the moſt part by reaſon of the <hi>Ignorance</hi> that is in them? Surely yes: for who now <hi>ſo bold as Blind Bayard?</hi> who ſo ſinfull as the Rude multitude? <hi>whoſe Cogitations being darkened, and hearts har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened, being paſt feeling, and giuen ouer to Wantonneſſe, doe worke all Vncleanneſſe with Greedineſſe</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Eph. 4.18.19.</note>. And therefore no maruell though <hi>Sinne Raigne in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But againe ſee how <hi>vnbeliefe</hi> drawes on to <hi>ſins Regencie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Vnbeliefe.</note> If the Deuill can but blinde this <hi>Eye of Faith,</hi> but pricke this <hi>Foot,</hi> lame this <hi>Hand;</hi> then he knowes that he ſhall quickly make vs, <hi>Eye</hi> all ſinne, <hi>Goe</hi> vnto all iniquitie, and <hi>Reach</hi> after all wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: <hi>That</hi> indeed is it that draweth Gods wrath, haſteneth Gods iudgements, depriueth vs of Gods promiſes, and nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth his couenants. Faiths <hi>Neceſſuie</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 11.6.</note> implies <hi>vnbeliefes Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,</hi> makes it worthy of none other King then <hi>ſinne,</hi> to whoſe Lawes they muſt yeeld, and to whoſe Luſts they muſt obey; for it is their <hi>King,</hi> and therefore it will <hi>Raigne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let vs ſee how <hi>Cuſtome</hi> preuailes for <hi>ſins Domination;</hi>
               <note place="margin">3 Cuſtome.</note> ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly much euery way. <hi>In familiaritatem grauiſſima adducit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Seneca de Tranquilitate vitae.</note>; Cuſtome makes heauie things light: It makes <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mels</hi> ſeeme <hi>Gnats;</hi> and <hi>Beames</hi> but <hi>Moates.</hi> The ſinner accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſinne is then in his <hi>Element,</hi> when he is committing hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and hiddeous crimes, groſſe and grieuous iniquities. And it is a Rule in <hi>Philoſophy; That no element is heauie ſo long as it is in its owne Sphere. Et Peccata quamuis Magna et Horrenda, cum
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2990:12"/>in Conſuetudine venerint, aut Parua aut nulla crediderunt,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Aug. Encheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dion. cap. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note>: And Sinne though horrid, and horrible, when men are <hi>Accuſtomed</hi> vnto it, ſeeme but ſmall, nay none at All; yea, Sinne that preſſe and ſincke downe ſome to hell, men accuſtomed therewith, will goe away as nimblie with it, as euer <hi>Sampſon</hi> did with the <hi>Gates, Poſts and Barres of Azzah</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Iudges 16.3.</note>, without complaint of any heaft at all: and that makes it raigne.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>Securitie</hi> hath an hand to helpe <hi>ſinne</hi> in its <hi>Regencie:</hi>
               <note place="margin">4 Securitie.</note> This <hi>Eaſe-full</hi> ſleepe in ſinne (which the <hi>Greeke Poets</hi> call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Deaths</hi> brother, or if you wil, a <hi>dead ſleepe,</hi>) this I ſay ſettles ſinne in its throne, yea, and brings him that is poſſeſſed therewith <hi>To ſit in his ſeate,</hi> as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> hath it<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 1.1.</note>, <hi>id eſt, ſecuré et pertenaciter perſeuerare in delictis, et omnem Pietatem et Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem habere pro Ludibrio</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Mollerus in loc.</note>: that is, ſecurely and obſtinately to perſeuere and continue in omiſſion of good duties, making a mocke of all piety and religion. This <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus ſoporis, Spirit of ſlumber,</hi> or as <hi>Piſcator</hi> tranſlateth it<note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 11.8. <hi>Piſc. in Loc.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>Dead ſleepe or ſenſeleſſe ſtumber</hi> poſſeſſing vs, doth make vs to thinke, <hi>Who is the Lord? or what can he doe?</hi> yea, and to ſay alſo; <hi>Wee haue made a Couenant with Death, and an Agreement with Hell, Though a Scourge runne ouer, and paſſe through, yet it ſhall not come at vs</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Iſay. 28.15.</note>. Yea, and <hi>this</hi> indeed hath beene it, which hath brought vs in ſuch ſubiection vnto <hi>ſinnes Dominion. This</hi> hath made vs now, like the <hi>Romanes</hi> of old, euen <hi>to ſinne,</hi> and <hi>to Fauour ſuch as doe it</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 1.32.</note>; both by Counſelling and Countenancing, by Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and Commending, by Prouocation and Silence, by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaritie and Defence. Oh this hath brought vs to Ripeneſſe of ſinne, and then what can wee looke for but the hooke of Gods iudgements to cut vs downe and plucke vs off? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs all <hi>ſtand</hi> in <hi>Awe</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>: Suſpect our owne corruptions, and be carefull in euery action to ſhun and auoyd the offence and diſpleaſing of God, then though <hi>ſinne</hi> hath <hi>Reſidencie</hi> in vs in <hi>Infirmitie,</hi> yet it ſhall not <hi>Raigne</hi> ouer vs with groſle <hi>Enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:</hi> Be wee therefore admoniſhed by Chriſt, which here bids <hi>vs ſinne no More.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhould now deſcend to the Reaſons, but me thinkes I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not let paſſe without obſeruation that which is implied in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2990:13"/>this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Ne amplius, No more:</hi> and that is this, <hi>That he had ſinned before, and ſo was ſicke;</hi> yea, take the Text in its <hi>Totum</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Diuiſion,</hi> and you ſhall ſee it wholly implied, yea, the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned haue concluded, <hi>That it was the Scope and Drift of Chriſts Conference with this man in the Temple, to ſhew him the firſt effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cauſe of his ſickneſſe</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Hugh Card. Ludolphus de Saxonia. Chemnitius. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. Caluinus. Aretius. Marloratus. Maldonatus. in locum.</note>, which was none other but <hi>ſinne;</hi> ſo that the Inference is plaine, to wit, <hi>That ſickneſſe, For, ſinne doth follow ſickneſſe In ſinne,</hi> or <hi>that Weakeneſſe of Bodie doth proceede from Wickedneſſe of Soule.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label>
            </p>
            <p>This is the <hi>Reall</hi> and <hi>Radicall</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Fons et mali, et morbi, et mortis. Aretius in Loc. Prima et princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pua cauſa Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatum. Strige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius. in Pſal. <hi>107</hi> Omnis Poena, Peccatum habet Antecedens. Aretu Problem. lrc. <hi>162.</hi> p. <hi>489.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>cauſe</hi> of all bodily ſickneſſes. For as the Naturaliſt ſaid: <hi>Ex ſanitate Anima ſit ſanitas Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Ariſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>meta-Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſic. lib. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note>; That the Soules ſoundneſſe was the bodies ſafetie; ſo De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines hold, <hi>That if the ſoule had not ſinned, the Body had not ſmarted. That</hi> Pernitious Parent hath begotten this dangerous and deadly ofspring; yea, from this Roote and impure Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie hath ſprung all our woefull Miſerie, taking from vs <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice,</hi> and making vs <hi>Pilgrims;</hi> bereauing vs of <hi>Immortalitie</hi> and putting on vs <hi>Mortalitie;</hi> diſpoſſeſſing vs of <hi>Gladneſſe</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing vs to <hi>Sadneſſe:</hi> and this doth the Scripture euery where teſtifie. <hi>Fooles are afflicted</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi>) Why? <hi>Becauſe of their offences.</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 107.17.</note> And <hi>Ezechiel</hi> prophecying of <hi>Iſraels</hi> Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and fearefull Ruine, layes downe this as the maine cauſe, euen <hi>Her Iniquitie,</hi> yea, ſo ſaith the Text; <hi>For this Ruine is for their Iniquitie</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Ezec. 7.19.</note>. Againe, <hi>I will ſwite thee</hi> (ſaith <hi>God</hi> to <hi>Iacob.</hi>) <hi>yea, I will make thee ſicke in ſmiting thee, and in making thee Deſolate;</hi> and why? <hi>Becauſe of thy ſinnes</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Micha. 6.13.</note>. And <hi>Eccleſiaſticus</hi> ſaying is not to be buried in ſilence, who ſaith: <hi>That hee that finneth before his maker,</hi> ſhall <hi>fall into the hands of the Phiſitian</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Ecclus 38.16.</note>, and ſo did this man without doubt: For me thinkes it could no otherwiſe be, but that he who was ſicke 38. yeares, ſhould (with that woman, <hi>Marke</hi> 5.25.26. ſicke of the bloudy <hi>Iſſue</hi> 12. <hi>yeares</hi>) <hi>ſuffer many things of the Phyſitians.</hi> Of all which painefull effects of <hi>Sinne,</hi> we may make plentifull vſe to bring vs vnto <hi>Sanctitie.</hi> As,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Firſt, it may teach vs to <hi>Abhorre Sinne aboue all things.</hi> By Nature we hate euery thing that Hurteth vs, how much more ſhould we <hi>Abhorre Sinne</hi> that woundeth vs ſo ſorely as it doth? <hi>Her way</hi> (like the way of a Strumpet) <hi>leades downe to Death and her footſteps take hold of Hell</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Prou. 5.5.</note>. Yea, ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard, Via
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2990:13"/>Peccati Ingredientes Contaminat; Progredientes obſtinat; Egredien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes exterminat</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Bern. in Senten</note>. Sinne in the firſt Entrance thereinto Defileth; in the <hi>Progreſſe</hi> Hardeneth; at its Going out Deſtroyeth. If I might with patience follow an <hi>Ancient</hi>
               <note n="v" place="margin">Beda lib. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortat. <hi>4.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note>, in Sinnes diſcription, I thinke it would (if any thing would) make vs to <hi>abhorre</hi> it.</p>
            <p>Hee termes it a <hi>Monſter,</hi> yea, and not onely ſo, but alſo <hi>A monſtrous Witch;</hi> which ſaith he, <hi>In tot Monſtra te transformat in quot Peccata te alterat;</hi> cauſeth thee to accept the reſemblance of ſo many Beaſts, as it maketh thee to attempt ſinnes. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; let it bring thee <hi>to fleſhly pleaſure,</hi> It will change thee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an <hi>Hogge,</hi> an <hi>Horſe,</hi> a <hi>Syren,</hi> a <hi>Sparrow:</hi> Or let it leaue thee to <hi>Sloath;</hi> then it will metamorphize thee into an <hi>Oſtridge,</hi> an <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant,</hi> a <hi>Cammell,</hi> a <hi>Dragon,</hi> an <hi>Aſſe:</hi> Or let it poſſeſſe thee with <hi>Couetouſneſſe,</hi> and then no <hi>Harpie</hi> ſhall be compared vnto thee, though <hi>inſatiable in Coneting, ſwift in Purſuing, hard in Holding:</hi> Or let <hi>Crueltie</hi> take hold of thee, and then no <hi>Hiena,</hi> no <hi>Wolfe,</hi> no <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iper,</hi> ſhall be able to match thee. <hi>Oh monſtrum miſerabile!</hi> Oh miſerable monſter, oh bewitched Sinner, who art ſo <hi>Taken</hi> (as they ſay) with ſuch a Witch as makes thee ſo foule in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo monſtrous in Mortalitie, ſo damnable in Diuinitie! Sinne, it will not onely make thee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Impium &amp; improbum,</hi> void of holineſſe and honeſty for a time, but it will change thee into <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Inſignem Nebulonem</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Iohn 9.16. <hi>Aretius in Loc.</hi>
               </note>, a notable, notorious, a palpable, apparent, groſſe and gricuous ſinner: yea, into one whoſe <hi>Eyes</hi> ſhall be full of <hi>Adulterie;</hi> whoſe <hi>Eares</hi> ſhall be open to all <hi>vaine delights;</hi> whoſe <hi>Tongue</hi> ſhall be ſwollen with <hi>Deceipt;</hi> whoſe <hi>Lips</hi> ſhall be boulſtred with the <hi>Poyſon of Aſpes;</hi> whoſe <hi>Throate</hi> ſhall be <hi>an open Sepulchre;</hi> whoſe <hi>Hands</hi> ſhall be full of <hi>Briberie;</hi> whoſe <hi>Belly</hi> a <hi>timpany of Gluttonie;</hi> whoſe <hi>Backe</hi> ſhall be loaden with <hi>Idleneſſe;</hi> and whoſe <hi>Feete</hi> ſhall be ſwift (enought though) <hi>to ſhed bloud.</hi> Loe then, <hi>Sinne</hi> being ſuch a thing as will make thee ſuch an one, who will not <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre It</hi> aboue all things? Yea indeede, let vs not loue that which cauſeth God to loath vs, let vs not ſwill downe that which maketh God to ſwell againſt vs, making vs <hi>ſicke</hi> becauſe of <hi>ſinne,</hi> and <hi>Weake</hi> by reaſon of <hi>Wickedneſſe:</hi> but rather as I haue ſaid already, let vs <hi>Abhorre</hi> it.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:2990:14"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> But againe, <hi>Doth Sinne cauſe ſickneſſe?</hi> Then let this teach vs <hi>to commiſerate and pittie men in their ſinfull eſtates, as well as in their ſickly.</hi> In viſiting the <hi>ſicke, Ah my Brother, and alas my Siſter,</hi> are the vſuall ſtraines, but comming to our <hi>ſinfull ſoules</hi> and ſeeing them <hi>ſicke</hi> with <hi>ſinne, euen vnto Death,</hi> we cannot mourne, nor pittie them, nay rather we reioyce and ſing. Which may I not with <hi>Solomon,</hi> call <hi>A mad mirth</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Eccleſ. 2.2.</note>? Surely yes. For who would cenſure more charitablie of that man, who when hee is called to the houſe of mourning, wherein his <hi>Deareſt friend</hi> lyes lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing, he in ſtead of <hi>Mourning, laugheth, reioyceth and danceth for ioy?</hi> And what ſhall we thinke of ſuch as are <hi>Dying</hi> with <hi>ſinne;</hi> yea, <hi>Dead</hi> in <hi>ſinne: Deadly Drunke, Deadly Couetous,</hi> whom when wee eſpie, wee laugh at them? But let all ſuch Reioycers take heed, and Repent of this their pitteous Mirth, leſt they pertake of that woe which our Sauiour hath denounced, ſaying, <hi>Wee be vnto them which now laugh,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Luk. 6.25.</note> 
               <hi>for they ſhall weepe and houle</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">z</hi>.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Thirdly, doth <hi>Wickedneſſe</hi> cauſe <hi>Weakeneſſe?</hi> Then let this teach vs to <hi>acknowledge without murmuring, that all the iudgements which ſeaze on vs, are iuſt and righteous altogether.</hi> Two peere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe patternes hereof we haue in ſacred Write, the firſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is the <hi>Widdow of Sareptah,</hi> whoſe <hi>Sonne falling ſicke,</hi> yea, <hi>euen ſicke vnto Death; ſo that</hi> (as the Text ſaith) <hi>There was no Breath in him</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 Kin. 17.17.18.</note>, She murmures not, ſhe repines not, ſhe reuiles not the man of God, but rather diſprayſeth her ſelfe, imputeth her Childes ſickneſſe and death vnto her ſelfe, ſaying: <hi>Art thou come to call my ſinne to remembrance, and to ſlay my Sonne?</hi> Which had beene as much as if ſhe had ſaid: <hi>Oh man of God, I humbly acknowledge that it were iuſt with God if he did call my ſinnes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, and for puniſhment of them did take away my Sonne, I had no cauſe to murmure, but rather to mourne, becauſe my ſinne is ſo great as to deſerue this, yea, and many more heauie puniſhments then this.</hi> Loe, ſhe is not like <hi>Veſpatian,</hi> who being <hi>ſicke</hi> and out of hope of life, threw the Curtaines aſide, ſpreading his hands, and complaining againſt his Gods, <hi>Se Immerenti ſibi vitam eripi</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Sac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onius in v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſp. cap. <hi>10</hi>
               </note>; That they tooke away his life without any fault or fayling on his part: No, no, ſhe doth not behaue her ſelfe any whit fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, but humbly acknowledgeth <hi>that her ſinnes haue deſerued it.</hi> The like we may reade of in the booke of <hi>Nehemiah:</hi> How
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2990:14"/>the <hi>Leuites</hi> laid open the ſinnes of the whole land, <hi>Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning themſelues,</hi> and <hi>Commending the Lord.</hi> Confeſſing his <hi>kindneſſe</hi> vnto <hi>Them,</hi> and their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkindneſſe</hi> vnto <hi>Him.</hi> Yea, <hi>ſurely</hi> (ſay they) <hi>Thou art iuſt in all that is come vpon vs: Thou haſt dealt truely, but we haue done wickedly</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Neh. 9.33.</note>. And thus it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth vs to doe likewiſe, euen in all our Troubles and Afflictions that befall vs in this life, therewith to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and willingly to ſubiect our ſelues vnto Gods will, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently wayting his leiſure, and ſo doing let vs not doubt but that at the laſt the Lord will come, yea, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence his ſeeming ſlackneſſe with plenty of ioy and glory, and honour and immortalitie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> Fourthly, what though <hi>ſickneſſe commeth for ſinne</hi> yet let vs not <hi>vncharitably conclude (though God may know it to be true,) That euery one that we ſee grieuouſlie ſicke, is a Grieuous ſinner:</hi> or, <hi>That he or his friends haue deſerued ſuch a ſickneſſe, or ſuch a plague, or ſuch a puniſhment:</hi> No let vs leaue this to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> or put it off to the <hi>Barbarians.</hi> The firſt whereof would needes vncharitablie cenſure <hi>The man that was borne blinde,</hi> and would not be perſwaded but <hi>That either Hee, or his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents had ſinned,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 9.2.</note> that is, had extraordinarily ſinned aboue others. Againe, the <hi>Barbarians</hi> did no leſſe vnto <hi>Paul,</hi> on whoſe hand <hi>becauſe a Viper hung</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Acts 18.4.5.</note>, it could not be but that <hi>This man muſt be ſome Murtherer, who though he had eſcaped the Sea, yet Vengeance would not ſuffer him to Liue,</hi> ſaid they. A note which I haue heard ſome of our <hi>Pure-ſpirited Illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates</hi> too often and odiouſly ſing, yea and I haue heard them too, like <hi>Iobs Miſerable Comforters</hi> and mercileſſe friends, ſay both of, and <hi>vnto</hi> their afflicted brethren; <hi>That God had forgotten them for their Iniquities</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Iob 11.6.</note>, and <hi>That their wickedneſſe is Great, and their Iniquitie Innumerable</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Iob 22.5.</note>. But what art thou that <hi>Iudgeſt another mans ſeruant?</hi> or <hi>Who hath knowne the minde of God at any time?</hi> Canſt thou tell whether the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which thy brother ſuffereth, be a Probation or a Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Knoweſt thou the end of Gods doings? It may be his ſickneſſe is for the ſame end that <hi>Iobs</hi> afflictions were, euen <hi>to Try him, that he may come forth like the Gold</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Iob 23.10.</note>: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpare thy ſpeech, ſaue thy breath, looke to thy ſelfe and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2990:15"/>be more Charitable towards him. Is he now in his fiery try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, in the furnace of affliction? <hi>Hodie Mihi, Cras Tibi,</hi> this is his portion to day, it may be thy pittance to morrow. Hee it may be is in the furnace of Loue, when thou ſhalt be in the ouen of Wrath, therfore <hi>Thou that ſtandeſt take heede leſt that thou fall</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.12.</note>, and thou that now cenſureſt thine afflicted bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, beware leſt the ſame, if not worſe things, come vnto thee. Leſt therefore thy ſoule pay the price of thy tongue, be not ſo haſtie nor harſh againſt thy Brother in his heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but rather mourne with him, pray for him, <hi>That God</hi> (according to his promiſe) <hi>Would not lay vpon him more then he is able to beare,</hi> and in ſo doing thou ſhalt ſhew thy ſelfe, wiſe, honeſt, charitable and Chriſtian-like.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>5</label> Now in the next place, it may be you will expect ſome Comfort. But how can you looke for <hi>Grapes</hi> from <hi>Thornes?</hi> for <hi>Water</hi> from the <hi>Rocke?</hi> for <hi>Oyle</hi> from <hi>Stones?</hi> for <hi>Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> from <hi>Bitterneſſe?</hi> or for <hi>Comfort</hi> from <hi>Sinne?</hi> Yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and ſee, admire, and be thankefull to the God of might and Father of Mercie, that doth thus bring good out of euill, and that thus:</p>
            <p>He maketh <hi>Nocumenta</hi> to be <hi>Documenta,</hi> euen his Laſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to be Leſſenings: In Conſideration whereof Saint <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> did thanke God that he was <hi>Sicke;</hi> for, ſaith he, <hi>Detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta Corporis,</hi> were <hi>Incrementa Virtutis,</hi> my bodies Paine, was my ſoules Gaine, my Bed of ſickneſſe was my ſchoole and Doctorall Chayre of learning and diſcipline. Likewiſe it is reported of <hi>Nazianzine</hi> that hee tooke that comfort of his ſickneſſe, that in the middeſt thereof he ſaid: <hi>Morbe crucier et Gaudeo, non quia Crucior, ſed vt Alys Patientiaeſim Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter:</hi> That is, I am grieuouſly grieued and I reioyce, not that I am grieued, but that in the middeſt thereof, I behaue my ſelfe ſo, as that I may be a Patterne of patience to others: yea, and ſurely ſome ſuch haue I (to my vnſpeakeable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort) viſited, whoſe ſickneſſe hath beene ſo ſeaſoned with holy and ſanctified ſpeeches, that they haue oft preuented me, and in ſtead of receiuing comfort from my mouth, they haue giuen mee comfort to my ſoule: And their ſickneſſe like <hi>Lazarus</hi> his <hi>ſleepe</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. 11.11.</note>, haue not beene <hi>vnto Death, but for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2990:15"/>the Glory of God</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Verſe 4.</note>. For in it their Tongues haue beene as the Tongues of the learned, touched with a Coale from the Altar; their mouths haue ſpoken powerfull, pleaſant and profitable things, yea, and in it wee haue perceiued ſuch a meaſure of grace in them, as in thoſe who haue had their ſoules wayned from the world, their fleſh mortified, their ſpirits conſecrated to God, and themſelues rapt vp vnto the third heauens: Oh what comfort is here for the <hi>Sicke,</hi> though as <hi>Sicke</hi> as <hi>Sinfull!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Laſtly, <hi>is Sinne the cauſe of Sickeneſſe?</hi> how ſhould this preſſe forward men of place and authority, in Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, to ſet themſelues to the ſuppreſſing of ſinne? Surely much euery way.<note place="margin">1 Miniſters.</note> It ſhould make vs Miniſters to be euen <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>fily Tonituri, Sonnes of Thunder</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Marke 3.17.</note>, ratling from heauen the terrible iudgements of God againſt ſinners; yea, we ſhould be heard aboue, and be ſeene beneath, we ſhould out-face ſinne, out-preach it, out-liue it, ſuffering our light ſo to ſhine in the faces of worldlings, as that it might dazle them, whom it cannot guide, for <hi>Then</hi> and neuer till <hi>Then, Cum Imperio docetur, quod prius agitur quam dicatur</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Greg. in Job.</note>: Then (ſaith Saint <hi>Gregory</hi>) ſhal we with Authority ſpeake what we doe, when we doe what we ſpeake: And that done, by vs, will be but to little purpoſe, leſt you alſo that are authorized among the Commons, vnſheath your ſwords, and bend your bowes,<note place="margin">2 Magiſtrates.</note> to cut downe and ſhoot at thoſe rebellious wickedneſſes which be ſo preiudiciall to our peace, and ſuch a bane to our health here, and happineſſe hereafter. The ſinnes that cauſe theſe things are innumerable; Sinnes of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie and ſinnes of enormitie, ſinnes ſecret and ſinnes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and publike; yea, and thoſe capitall, crying ones too. For the ſuppreſſing of which if you doe not the ſooner and ſoarer lay too your hand, it is to be feared that the hand of God will ere long be vpon you and yours, vs and ours, <hi>Viſiting our Tranſgreſſions with the Rod, and our Iniquities with ſtroakes</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 89.32.</note>. The Crying ſinnes that we cry vnto you for ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing (among many) are ſpecially three. Firſt, <hi>Swearing.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Sabboth-breaking.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Drunkenneſſe.</hi> Which for want of Magiſtrates, who <hi>Phineas-like</hi> are <hi>Bold-countenanced,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:2990:16"/>they grow ſo bold as to ſtep into high places, and among high perſons, yea, and canker-like they ſpread further and further in the body of our ſtate, ſo that if thoſe members which are already infected, be not either cured by Gods Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, or cut off by our lawfull Magiſtrates, it is to be feared that they will grow deſperate and paſt hope of any cures of which behold a ſhrewd ſigne,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> for <hi>Swearing</hi> is now but the <hi>Gentlemans Grace of ſpeech,</hi> the <hi>Pages Complement,</hi> the <hi>Seruing-mans Sword,</hi> the <hi>Tradeſ-mans broaker,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Country-mans Yea,</hi> and <hi>Nay,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Againe, for <hi>Sabboth-breaking,</hi> why that is but the <hi>Citties day of Dalliance and Delight, Pride and Gluttouie;</hi> and the <hi>Country-mans Leiſure-day,</hi> wherein if they ſhould not <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create</hi> themſelues in <hi>Dauncing, Dicing, Drinking,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>Deuilliſh paſtimes,</hi> they would thinke themſelues much wrong'd.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Laſtly, for <hi>Drunkenneſſe,</hi> Why? that is but <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellowſhip, and Merry meeting, a Paſſing away the time to Laugh and be fat.</hi> But why ſhould theſe things be ſuffer'd by you, ſeeing that the Lawes of God and man, yea, lawes tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and eccleſiaſticall, haue ſo holily and wholeſomely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided a remedy? Your place requireth <hi>That ye be men of Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage; fearing God, dealing truely with all men</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Exod. 18.21.</note>, and therefore I beſeech you ſee to your Calling, and as you tender the health of our Country, the long biding, and well-being of our Church, ſet an edge on your ſwords, ſharpen your arrowes, bend your bowes, and good lucke haue you in the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Iuſtice on ſuch as thus notoriouſly offend, euen of pride and malitious wickedneſſe; The day be yours, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour be Gods, and the good be vnto vs and ours, from this time forward vnto the worlds end. And ſo much of the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition</hi> or <hi>Iniunction, Sinne no more.</hi> Now to the Reaſons, and that firſt of the firſt of them, drawne as I told you <hi>A Priore, or a Collocato Beneficio,</hi> from a good turne beſtowed; in theſe words: <hi>Thou art Whole, Therefore ſinne no more.</hi> Wherein are to be conſidered. 1. A worke wrought, <hi>Thou art whole,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pars ſecunda. Ratio Prima.</note> a worke of <hi>Health.</hi> 2. The Worker, cloſely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in that participle <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Pars prima, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me rationis.</note> 
               <hi>thou art MADE whole.</hi> Of theſein their order, and firſt of the worke. <hi>Thou art whole, Therefore ſinne no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:2990:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Benefits</hi> (ſaith our Prouerbe) <hi>are Binders. Et ownes Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorem Beneficy oderunt</hi> (ſaith the Oratour<note n="o" place="margin">Cicero de Offic. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note>,) And <hi>All</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the Heathen) hate vnthankefull perſons, much more Chriſtians, and moſt of all this man, who was ſo long ſicke, and ſo lowe brought as that hee could not <hi>Steppe into the Poole</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Verſe 7.</note>, he being ſo miraculouſly healed of ſuch an inueterat diſeaſe, yea, and that at ſuch a time as he, nor any of the Iewes would haue thought off, euen <hi>On the Sabboth</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Verſe 10.</note>. What leſſe ſacrifice can he offer? what better ſeruice can hee performe, then that which the Phyſitian both of ſoule and body doth require? and that is, <hi>becauſe he is made whole, he ſhould Sinne no more.</hi> Hence I inferre this Concluſion:<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>That our deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance from any yoake of Bondage, either of Sinne, or Sinnes Conſequence, (which is Sickeneſſe, Miſery, and Trouble) ſhould be a ſtrong bond binding Vs to the ſeruice of God, Thou art whole, Therefore Sinne no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Scripture is plentifull in the proofe of this; <hi>Zachari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> ſingeth it, and the Apoſtles ſay it: <hi>That being deliuered, &amp;c. Wee ſhould ſerue him in Holineſſe and Righteouſneſſe</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Luke 1.74.75</note>. <hi>That be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing freed from Sinne, we ſhould be made the ſeruants of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">Rom. 6.18.</note>. <hi>That being bought with a Price, wee ſhould glorifie God</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.20.</note>. <hi>That the Grace of God hauing appeared, it ſhould teach vs to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Vngodlines, &amp;c</hi>
               <note n="v" place="margin">Tit. 2.11, 12.</note>. Yea, it is the Cord &amp; Cart-rope wherwith and wherby God would both draw and bind his people to obedience: It is the ſtring that he harpes vpon ſeauen times, yea the burthen of his ſong, almoſt in euery place, or at leſt in euery booke of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> ſaying: <hi>I haue brought thee out of the Land of Egypt, and redeemed thee out of the houſe of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, &amp;c. Therefore, thou ſhalt haue none other Gods but mee</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 20.2.3. Deut. 5.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore ye ſhall keepe my Commandements</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Leuit. 22.18.31.16.13.</note>. <hi>Therefore ſhall yee eate the Paſſeouer vnto the Lord your God</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Deut. 4.37.40.7.8.11. Deut. 16.1, 2, <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </note>, yea, and <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould this man Sinne no more,</hi> becauſe <hi>He is made whole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And reaſon good. For <hi>who</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>planteth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Vineyard and eateth not the fruit thereof</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.7.</note>? and why ſhould God, plant and place vs in a fruitfull <hi>Canaan?</hi> why ſhould he helpe and heale vs in ſickneſſe and diſtreſſe, if after all this we ſhall <hi>Sinne yet more, and more,</hi> in ſtead of <hi>Sinning no more?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This meetes with that in-bred,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> and ouer-ſpred corruption
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2990:17"/>of ours which takes ſuch liberty to it ſelf of ſinning, becauſe God is mercifull, as it is wonderfull to behold.</p>
            <p>True it is <hi>That Grace hath abounded,</hi> what? <hi>Shall we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore continue in Sinne?</hi> Tis as true, <hi>That we alſo are healed,</hi> what ſhall we therefore ſinne? ſhall wee make no better vſe of Gods mercies? God forbid.</p>
            <p>Know thou oh Chriſtian whatſoeuer thou art, <hi>That Grace doth not giue the reines to Licentiouſneſſe of Life,</hi> but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>It is the ſtreighteſt bridle to hold vs from all ſinne. Dauid</hi> makes it the End of Gods mercy, <hi>Not to be ſecure,</hi> but rather <hi>to feare</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 130.4.</note>: and the Apoſtle in all thoſe praiſes of Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies towards man makes no ſuch vſe, neither giues any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of diſpenſation to ſinne, but rather doth much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the Libertines and Epicures, which draw ſuch Sata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall concluſions out of ſuch Sanctified premiſes. But I haſten to ſpeake of the worker, or Author of this worke, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in this Participle,<note place="margin">Pars ſecunda, primae rationis.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. MADE <hi>whole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is worth our obſeruation, that Chriſt doth not here ſay <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Sanus es, Thou art whole. Ex Tui gratia, or Ex Tui potentia,</hi> out of thine owne merit or power; but hee ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Sanus Factus es, thou art</hi> MADE <hi>whole. De re facta loquitur</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Hugo Cardin. in Locum.</note>, he ſpeakes of the cure done <hi>On</hi> him, not <hi>By</hi> him. For if he could haue lept into the Poole, or haue had any to put him in at the <hi>Troubling of the Waters,</hi> he had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſtaid for Chriſts comming: But now that this mans <hi>Weakeneſſe</hi> and Gods <hi>Power,</hi> his <hi>Miſerie</hi> and Gods <hi>Mercy,</hi> might at once be manifeſted, Chriſt tels the man that he was MADE <hi>whole.</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> Whence we are taught, <hi>That when God doth worke any thing either In, Vpon, or By vs, we ought not to attribute it to our ſelues, but vnto God onely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be demaunded, <hi>Whence commeth our Helpe? Dauid</hi> will tell vs, <hi>That it commeth from the Lord, which hath made heauen and earth</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal 121.2.</note>. Againe, <hi>Are Kings ſaued by the Multitude of an Hoaſt</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 33.16.</note>? why then did not that <hi>Multitude of the Midianites, who lay like Graſhoppers vpon the earth, and whoſe Cammels were numberleſſe</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Iudg. 7.12.</note>? why did not they ſaue themſelues and deſtroy Iſrael? Thirdly, <hi>Are mighty men deliuered by their much ſtrength</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 33.16.</note>? why then did not <hi>Goliah,</hi> that <hi>Vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2990:17"/>Philiſtim,</hi> who came to <hi>Dauid</hi> with <hi>A Sword, a Speare</hi> and a <hi>Shield</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">1 Sam.17.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, to ouercome him that had onely <hi>A ſtaffe in his hand, fiue ſmooth ſtones, and a Sling</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Verſe 40.</note>? In a word, <hi>Are Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Helpes?</hi> Why then did not <hi>Pharaoh</hi> with his 600. <hi>Choſen Chariots, and All the Chariots of Egypt, ouercome, ouertake, and ouerthrow Iſrael</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Exod. <hi>14.</hi> a v. <hi>7.</hi> ad <hi>28.</hi>
               </note>? Why? euen becauſe <hi>The Lord was their Helpe, and their Shield,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 33.20.</note>: In Admiration whereof one both pithily, and pectorally ſaith; <hi>Oh beatos qui ab hoc ſolo Opitulatore pendent, &amp; ad hanc Anchoram ſalutis in Rebus aduerſis <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>era fiducia confugiunt</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Strigelius in Pſal <hi>121.</hi> p. <hi>479</hi> in <hi>8</hi>
               </note>: Oh happy are they that hang on his helpe, and that take hold on him, as the Anchor of their hope in all their ſtormes of aduerſitie and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But on the contrary, <hi>Oh miſeros quorum res exiguo filo pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, &amp; tantùm Praeſidijs humanis quae ſunt Euripo mobiliora</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Strigelius vbi ſupra.</note>. Oh vnhappy and miſerable creatures are they that hang by ſuch ſmall threds, and that onely truſt on humane helpes, which are more inconſtant then the Riuer <hi>Euripus,</hi> that ebbes and flowes ſeauen times a day. <hi>No, No, Sperent Alij in Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chium carnis, praeſument in ſuis Viribus</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Muſculus in Pſal.</hi> 33.16.20.</note>: Let others make fleſh their Arme, and boaſt of their great ſtrength, yet let vs put our truſt in the Name of the Lord, who onely is able to make vs whole.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Him</hi> onely had <hi>Iſrael</hi> helpe againſt the <hi>Philiſtines</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">1 Sam. 7.10.</note>. By <hi>Him</hi> alone had <hi>Dauid</hi> ſtrength againſt that <hi>Goliah</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">1 Sam. 17.50.</note>. By <hi>Him</hi> onely had the <hi>Shunamites ſonne Life</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">1 King. 4.36.</note>, and by <hi>Him</hi> and <hi>His Chriſt</hi> was this man <hi>made Whole</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Iohn 5.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That in <hi>Warres, Weapons</hi> ſhould be vſed; That in <hi>Hunger, Meate</hi> ſhould be prepared; That in <hi>Sickeneſſe, Phyſicke</hi> ſhould be adminiſtred, who denies? but if the <hi>Lord fight not,</hi> if the <hi>Lord feede</hi> not; if the <hi>Lord bleſſe</hi> not the meanes, we ſhall be <hi>Slaine</hi> all the ſort of vs: wee ſhall be <hi>Hungary</hi> ſtill, yea, and <hi>Languiſh</hi> euen vnto death: For ſo doth <hi>Maſter Caluin</hi> excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently note; ſaying; <hi>Donec Caleſtis medicus opem nobis fert, Nos non tantum intus fouemus multos morbos ſed etiam mortes</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cabin Pſal.</hi> 130.3.</note>, that is, Till that heauenly Phyſitian doth bring health, wee doe not onely cheriſh in vs many diſeaſes, but bring on our ſelues many deaths.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:2990:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Death Temporall, Death Spirituall, Death Eternall;</hi> By the firſt whereof we ſhall be depriued of life, by the ſecond, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned from grace, by the third, ſeparated from glory. Will we then be <hi>Cured,</hi> will we be <hi>Made whole,</hi> then let vs looke vp vnto God, beleeue in God, and depend on him, for hee onely it is that maketh vs to dwell in ſafetie.</p>
            <p>And good reaſon is there why we ſhould ſo doe,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> whether we regard our <hi>Selues,</hi> or reſpect <hi>God.</hi> Our weakeneſſe or <hi>His</hi> power. The one is ſuch as that we cannot <hi>Adde one Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite to our Stature</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Mat. 6.27.</note>, <hi>one Minute to our Dayes; one Moment to our Liues;</hi> yea, ſuch as that being <hi>Fallen</hi> we cannot <hi>Riſe;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Weake</hi> we cannot <hi>Strengthen</hi> our ſelues; being <hi>Sicke</hi> we cannot be <hi>Healed,</hi> yea, ſuch as <hi>Sowing Much ſhall reape but Little; Eating much ſhall not haue Enough, Drinking much ſhall not be Filled; Cloathing our ſelues cannot be Warmed, and Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning much Wages, ſhall but put it in a broken Bag</hi>
               <note n="v" place="margin">Haggai. 1.6.</note>, except the <hi>Lord</hi> puts to his hand, except the <hi>Lord</hi> addes a bleſſing.</p>
            <p>Yea,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label>, His honour and praiſe it is to acknowledge, <hi>That in the might of</hi> His <hi>power we are made Strong</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Epheſ. 6.10.</note>; <hi>That through Chriſt, Wee are ſtrengthned</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 8.37.</note>, That <hi>Corroboration</hi> is an hearoe of Grace <hi>that commeth from Aboue</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">I am. 1.17.</note>, <hi>That Eſtabliſhment comes from His free ſpirit</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Pſal. 51.12.</note>: any of all which if we attribute vnto our ſelues, wee Robbe God of his honour; If therefore we haue attained vnto, either ſafetie of body or ſaluation of ſoule, if we are healed of the ſoareneſſe of the one, or eaſed of the ſorrowfulneſſe of the other, let the praiſe and glory be <hi>Gods, who onely maketh vs whole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the vſe hereof; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> euen this, <hi>That when we heare that nothing is, or can be done, but by the might of Gods power, That then we make it, vt Machina ad Deſtruendam omnem Altitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem; Gladius ad Conſiciendam omnem Superbiam</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Caluin. in Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ip.</hi> 2.13.</note>, <hi>euen an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine to ouerthrow all high exaltings, and a Sword to cut downe, waſt, and conſume all Pride that is in vs.</hi> Yea, let it ſerue as an <hi>Axe</hi> to hew downe, and a <hi>Sawe</hi> to cut off that high exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of theirs who boaſt and ſay: <hi>We haue killed, or wee haue made aliue, We haue Saued, or we haue Deſtroyed:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>No, no,</hi> It is not <hi>Wee,</hi> but it is <hi>God</hi> that worketh, either IN
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2990:18"/>
               <hi>vs,</hi> or BY <hi>vs,</hi> FOR <hi>vs,</hi> or AGAINST <hi>vs.</hi> Therefore know thou oh thou mighty man whatſoeuer thou art, that whatſoeuer thou haſt done, thou are but the <hi>Axe</hi> and <hi>Sawe</hi> of the moſt mightie: Now ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Shall the Axe boaſt it ſelfe againſt him that heweth with it? Or ſhall the Sawe exalt it ſelfe againſt him that moneth it</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iſay. 10.15.</note>? No; <hi>Nec in vllo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> eſt, quia Noſtrum nihil eſt</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Cyprianus in epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. ad Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium.</note>: Neither ought wee to boaſt in any thing, becauſe nothing is our <hi>owne.</hi> For tell me, is the Praiſe of <hi>writing well</hi> the glory of the <hi>Penne?</hi> Or is the Praiſe of <hi>ſpeaking well</hi> the glory of the <hi>Tongue?</hi> Or is the Praiſe of <hi>doing-well</hi> the glory of the <hi>Hand?</hi> No verily, it is <hi>God that willeth, that worketh, that doth according to his good will and pleaſure</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Philip. 2.13.</note>. And whoſoeuer ſhall giue it to any other, let him be branded with the name of a Robber, and a Theefe; and of this ſo iealous is the Lord, as that he will giue it <hi>To none other</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Exod. 20.</note>. And therefore ſaith the holy Ghoſt; <hi>Left Iſraell ſhould vaunt it ſelfe againſt God and ſay, MINE hand hath ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Iudg. 7.2.</note>, the Lord would not ſuffer <hi>Gideon</hi> to goe forth with any more then <hi>Three hundred men of Iſrael</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">v. 6.8.</note>, againſt <hi>two and thirty thouſands of the Midianites, and they put them to flight</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">v. 22.</note>. And remember how hainouſly the Lord tooke it at <hi>Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzars</hi> hands, that hee ſhould ſo proudly vaunt and ſay: <hi>That HE had built an houſe by the Might of his power, and for the Honour of His Maieſtie</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Dan. 4.27.</note>. And no leſſe reproach was it vnto Chriſt, that <hi>Pilate</hi> ſhould ſay: <hi>That HE had power to Crucifir him, and HE had power to Looſe him</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Iohn 19.10.</note>. Might not a man ſay of his <hi>Exaltation,</hi> as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaid of <hi>Caines Deſperation</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Amb. in Gen. <hi>4.13.</hi>
               </note>? <hi>Mentiris Pilate,</hi> thou lyeſt <hi>Pilate:</hi> Surely yes, for as Chriſt hath it in the enſueing words, <hi>He could haue no power at all againſt him, except it were giuen him from Aboue</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Iohn 11.19.</note>: <hi>Imperium Malorum a Deo ſit,</hi> The wicked muſt know <hi>That there is no Power but of God</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 3.1.</note>, which though it be giuen them, <hi>Tamen nihil iuris habent in Sanctis niſi Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſione Diuina,</hi> yet they haue no right, no power ouer Gods Sonne, or Saints, or Seruants, but what is giuen of him<note n="o" place="margin">Aretius in Iohn <hi>19.11.</hi>
               </note>: therfore as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſweetly aduiſeth: <hi>Let man thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiue what God giues, and leaue that which he reſerues, leſt by
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2990:19"/>vſurping that which is denied, he deſerue to loſe that which is gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> Health and happineſſe is now <hi>Ours,</hi> let Honour and Praiſe be <hi>His.</hi> Through <hi>ſinne</hi> wee were all <hi>ſicke,</hi> but by the <hi>Mercies of God in Chriſt Ieſus we are made whole.</hi> Therefore let vs all remember our Recouerie with no leſſe thankes and praiſe to God then did the faithfull of old, who being freed from the oppreſſion of Idolatrous Tyrants cryed and ſaid: <hi>Not vnto Vs O Lord, not vnto Vs, but vnto Thy name be the praiſe</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 115.1.</note>, for though <hi>Wee</hi> haue ſinned, yet <hi>Thou</hi> haſt <hi>Made vs whole:</hi> and let this ſuffice for the firſt reaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Secundum mem. Partis primae Ratio ſecunda.</note>The ſecond followes. <hi>Leſt a worſe thing come vnto thee,</hi> drawne (as I haue already ſaid) <hi>A Poſteriori, or a Tergo, or A Terribili Comminatione:</hi> From an heauy threat of Gods vengeance. <hi>Leſt a worſe thing come, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the former Reaſon <hi>Mercie</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> met together, that by them this man might be reduced from <hi>ſinne,</hi> now <hi>Righteouſneſſe and Truth</hi> doe kiſſe each other, that he might be induced to <hi>Sanctitie;</hi> precedent mercie was Chriſt firſt cord to draw this man from ſinne: but if this will not ſerue, then behold his ſubſequent iuſtice which ſhall be as a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to binde him; yea, <hi>A worſe thing ſhall come vnto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sinne (as you haue already heard) is a ſickneſſe: Now in euery ſickneſſe by how much a Relaps is more perillous then the firſt diſeaſe (by reaſon that Strength is ſpent, and Nature made more weake,) by ſo much is the Relaps into ſinne more dangerous, then the firſt ſinning, becauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the ſtrength of grace is weakened, and the ſtocke of goodneſſe decayed, yea, in ſuch an one as continueth in his ſinne without remorſe, without ſorrow or ſhame after that he hath beene mercifully admoniſhed, and iuſtly puniſhed, In <hi>Him</hi> ſee how the ſparkes of goodneſſe lies a dying, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold how the Flouds of iniquitie ouer whelmes him, marke his ſoare aſſaults, either to <hi>Preſumption</hi> or <hi>Deſperation,</hi> and little ſtrength hath hee (God wot) to Reſiſt either; ſo that how can it be but <hi>That a worſe thing, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is well obſerued by a wittie <hi>Preacher of our</hi> times<note n="q" place="margin">Adams Blacke Deuill. p. <hi>73.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>That Impenitencie for the Former part of our life, doth beſpeake
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2990:19"/>Impudencie in the Latter end, and by often proſtitution of our Hearts vnto vncleanneſſe we get an Whores forehead</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Ier. 3.3.</note>, <hi>that cannot bluſh,</hi> ſo that <hi>A worſe thing cannot but come vnto vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Diuiſio ſecundae rationis</note>But let vs ſee the particulars of this ſecond reaſon alſo.</p>
            <p>And they are likewiſe two in number, to wit.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt the Certaintie. <hi>Leſt,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly the Extreamitie, a <hi>worſe,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prima pars ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunde rationis.</note>The firſt doth not here, as in other places, imply any vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaintie, likelihood, chance, or fortune: for marke the Text, which ſaith not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Imo niſi: Leſt Perhaps, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance or Peraduenture,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Luke 3.5.</note> but it ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>vt Ne: Leſt aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly it come to paſſe, as being a Iudgement proceeding from the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of lights, with whom there is no variableneſſe nor ſhaddow of change;</hi> Whence I conclude: <hi>That Puniſhment ſhal certainly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſin,</hi> or, <hi>That Sin and Puniſhments are inſeparable Companions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the one will goe before, the other ſhall follow after; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> If there be no remedie but that men will needes <hi>Sowe vnto Iniquitie,</hi> no maruell though the Harueſt come, though their ſinnes ripen, and that they <hi>Reape Affliction</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Prouer. 22.8.</note>; yea, ſo inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable are they, that the <hi>Hebrew-iſts</hi> call them by one and the ſame name; for where the Text ſaith; <hi>Sinne lieth at the doore</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 4.7.</note>; and againe, <hi>My ſinne is greater then I can beare</hi>
               <note n="v" place="margin">Verſe 13.</note>; and a third time; <hi>Your ſinne ſhall finde you out:</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Numb. 32.23 Pſal. 140.11.</note> There both <hi>Montanus</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Bib. Heb. in Gen. <hi>4.13.</hi> Punitio vt fera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note>, <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius and Tremelius</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Paenam peccati Metonymia.</note>, doe render it <hi>Puniſhment:</hi> whence they haue inferr'd as I haue done, <hi>That ſinne and puniſhment are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable companions,</hi> euen Brothers and Siſters, nay Mother and Daughter, yea Cauſe and effect, <hi>Entitie</hi> of <hi>Non Ens</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Nec ſimpliciter Nihil, nec pura et ſimple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> priua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, ſicu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mors eſt-priuatio vitae &amp;c ſed Defectus et Diſtructio rei po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſittuae &amp;c. Buchanus Loc. com. Loc. <hi>15.</hi> Quaeſt. <hi>7.</hi> p. <hi>167</hi>
               </note>, ſomething of Nothing, Affliction of Infection: yea, the <hi>Sunne</hi> and its <hi>Light; Fire</hi> and its <hi>Heate; Water</hi> and its <hi>Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture,</hi> nay, I will goe a ſtraine higher; and that is, <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Iuſtice</hi> may as well be ſeparated as <hi>Sinne</hi> and <hi>Deſert of Puniſhment.</hi> Of which if you would know the Reaſons, they are theſe:</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, to cleere his Iudgement and Iuſtice, that we ſhould know him to be no Reſpecter of perſons, but to hate ſinne, whenſoeuer; whereſoeuer, and in whomſoeuer he findes it.</item>
               <item>Secondly,<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> to manifeſt his mercies in that he giues his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2990:20"/>Children their portion here, that hee might receiue them hereafter.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Which being ſo, oh what ineſtimable comfort is here for Gods choſen? Though <hi>ſinne muſt be puniſhed</hi> yet thy <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (that art of God) ſhall be but as the <hi>Stripes of a Father, or Smitings of a Friend,</hi> euen <hi>gentle</hi> and <hi>eaſie. Iudgement</hi> thou muſt haue, becauſe (as thou haſt heard) it ſtandeth with his Iuſtice, but be not diſmayed with any feare, for in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the end of his iudging thee, thou maieſt haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, which is none other ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>But that thou maieſt not be condemned with the world</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.31.32.</note> 
               <hi>In Trouble, in Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, in Anguiſh, in Paine, in Loſſes, and in Croſſes,</hi> why art thou ſo caſt downe oh my ſoule, and why art thou ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted within me? Didſt thou euer ſee, heare or read of any of <hi>Gods Saints</hi> that were put in his <hi>Furnace</hi> which came not out againe? yea, looke on thoſe <hi>Saints</hi> that were <hi>Racked, and Mocked; Bound, and Impriſoned; Stoned and Hewen aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Tempted, and ſlaine with the ſword; That were Deſtitute, Afflicted, and tormented</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 11. a 33. ad 40.</note>; ſee if they obtained not the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and why then ſhouldeſt thou feare? <hi>Thou</hi> art per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps afflicted, <hi>why? What ſonne is it whom the Father Chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 12.7.</note>? It may be thou complaineſt that thou haſt, ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, mocking, and prophane Children, why ſo had <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> an <hi>Iſhmael</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 16.15.</note>, <hi>Noah</hi> a <hi>Cham</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 9.21.</note>, <hi>Iſaack</hi> an <hi>Eſau</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 25.25</note>: or it may be <hi>That cruell witneſſes haue riſen vp againſt thee, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the things thou kneweſt not,</hi> or, <hi>they haue rewarded thee euill for good, to haue ſpoyled thy ſoule;</hi> why, ſo had <hi>Dauid</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 35.11.12</note>: yea, and all the <hi>Worthies</hi> that euer were in the world haue drunk of this Cup of affliction, yet feare not, for they now Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue, what thou ſhalt aſſuredly poſſeſſe, euen <hi>The Cup of Refection,</hi> for they were puniſhed here, to be receiued here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, and ſo ſhalt thou be if thou will goe and <hi>Sinne no more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> But in the ſecond place let me demand, <hi>Is Sinne and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment inſeperable?</hi> Then tremble at this all yee <hi>vngodly.</hi> For what? <hi>Shall the Righteous be recompenced on the Earth?</hi> how much more the <hi>Wicked</hi> and <hi>ſinnefull</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Prou. 11.31.</note>? <hi>Will hee doe this
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2990:20"/>to the Greene tree? What ſhall be done to the Dry?</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Luke 23.31.</note> 
               <hi>Will he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to plague the Cittie, where his Name is called vpon, and ſhall you goe free?</hi> ſaith <hi>Ieremie</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Ier. 25.29.</note>. No, <hi>If iudgement begin at <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.17.18.</note>, then <hi>Horrendam Vltionem ijs inſtare, quorum nunc potior videtur conditio,</hi> ſaith M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Caluin</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Caluin Loc.</note>, they that obey not the Goſpell &amp; yet ſeeme proſperous, ſhall then be found in their condition moſt pittious. This is granted, <hi>That the Lord doth try the Righteous in his Furnace, but the wicked, and ſuch as loue Iniquitie doth his ſoule hate,</hi> yea, and on <hi>Them will hee raine Snares, Fire, and Brimſtone, Storme and Tempeſt, This ſhall be their portion to drinke</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 11.5.6.7</note>. Indeed he lifteth vp his hands to ſtrike the <hi>Faithfull,</hi> but hee will cruſh his Aduerſaries with a <hi>Scepter of Iron, and breake them in peeces like a Potters veſſell</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 2.9.</note>. Hee will <hi>iudge</hi> the <hi>Iuſt</hi> for his ſinnes in this life, but hee will <hi>wound the Hairy ſcalpe of ſuch an one as goeth on ſtill in his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 68.21.</note>. His little <hi>Finger</hi> ſhall be <hi>heauier</hi> on the <hi>Reprobate,</hi> then his <hi>Loynes</hi> on his <hi>owne People:</hi> Therefore I ſay, <hi>tremble at this all ye wicked,</hi> which walke inordinately, and yet ſay, <hi>Tuſh, God ſeeth not,</hi> or, <hi>Tuſh, God careth not for it</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 10.12.</note>, or, <hi>Tuſh, no harme ſhall happen vnto vs</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">v. 14.</note>.</p>
            <p>You Ignorant men and women, whoſe cry is; <hi>That twas neuer ſo bad a world as ſince there was ſo much Preaching,</hi> and you whoſe howling is after the <hi>Oynions</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the <hi>Maſſe</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Pax</hi> of old, the <hi>Crucifixe,</hi> the <hi>Durges</hi> and <hi>Latine Prayers:</hi> Yee that praiſe the plenty in time of <hi>Poperie,</hi> you that ſay, <hi>That you felt no euill when ye offered Cakes to the Queene of Heauen.</hi> Oh <hi>King of Heauen,</hi> forgiue your ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. What was it then a merry world when there was <hi>Monie</hi> and no <hi>Men?</hi> Was it a merry world when the <hi>Crucifixe</hi> was kiſſed and <hi>Chriſt</hi> was <hi>Crucified anew?</hi> Was it a merry world when <hi>Ignorance</hi> rid on horſe-backe and <hi>Knowledge</hi> went on foote? Mourne, oh mourne ye for your Ingratitude, and pray the Lord that your eyes may be opened to ſee your errour, and your hearts may be enlarged to giue God the praiſe due vnto his name, for that his Puniſhments haue not beene as our ſinnes, infinite, vnmeaſurable, vnſupportable. Againe, tremble at this all ye Drunkards, whoſe cry is like
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2990:21"/>the former, ſaying: <hi>What though ſome Good-fellowes die with the Cup and Pipe at their mouthes? What though others are ſtabbed in their Drunkenneſſe; yet tuſh, no ſuch harme ſhall happen vnto vs.</hi> But oh ye fooliſh, how long will ye loue fooliſhneſſe? And yee beaſts, how long will yee loue beaſtlineſſe? Tell me, Is not Gods ſeate in heauen? Is not his hand ſtretched out ſtill? Is not his Anger as hot, and the fire of his indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation as fierie and fierce againſt ſinners as euer it was? Surely yes. And why then ſhould you yet heale your ſoules ſoares with the ſalue of Securitie? Oh doe no more ſo foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly. for this ſinne (yea and all other) like its Author the Deuill is but a <hi>Lyar: Mentitur Peccatum vt fallat; Vitam pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licetur vt perimat,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Cyprianus l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b <hi>1.</hi> epiſt. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note>. It lies, that it may deceiue, it promiſeth life that it might inflict Death. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let the bitterneſſe of <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> make vs all diſtaſte the ſweetneſſe of <hi>Sinne.</hi> This <hi>Viper Sinne,</hi> doth indeede like that <hi>Viperous Serpent</hi> yeeld a tickling delight to all our outward ſences; but as ſoone as the infected blood comes to the heart, preſently the body is in danger of death: yea, and ſo is our ſoule too if we doe not the ſooner ſee to it, and the more vigilantly watch ouer it. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi Peccatum; ibi Procella</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ryſ. hom. <hi>5.</hi> ad Populum Antioch.</note>. Where ſinne Raignes, there the wrath of God will tempeſtuouſly beate on vs; Say ſinne therefore what it will, beleeue thou the word of God which ſaith <hi>The wages of ſinne is Death</hi>
               <note n="v" place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note>, beleeue thou the well experienced in godlineſſe which ſaith. <hi>Dulce Peccatum, Amara Mors</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Author incog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitus.</note>, that no other fruit is to be pluckt from that Forbidden tree; then pale, blacke, gaſtly, and ghoſtly Death. <hi>Hoc agitur, Haec patitur,</hi> this is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that ſhall certainely be impoſed. <hi>Adam and Eue haue eaten of the tree of knowledge of good and euill, and haue died the death</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note>, And his poſteritie that ſhall ſinne, yea, ſecurely ſinne without feare of Iudgement paſt or to come, may cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely expect and aſſuredly looke for <hi>worſe things to happen to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo much for the Certainty of the Puniſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Secunda pars Secundae rationis</note>Now followes the Extreamitie. <hi>A worſe thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſubiect that I am to ſpeake of is <hi>Sickeneſſe</hi> ſtill, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2990:21"/>therefore blame me not if I follow the <hi>Phyſitians</hi> as well in their <hi>Proportion</hi> as in their <hi>Potion,</hi> in their <hi>Quantitie</hi> as in their <hi>Qualitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phyſitians</hi> if they meete with a body hard to worke vpon, they double their <hi>Doſſes,</hi> and vſe more violent meanes: So will the Lord deale with ſinners, when hee findes them ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate. If <hi>Peſtilence that walketh in darkeneſſe</hi> will not affright them; then let them look for <hi>Plagues deſtroying at Noone-day</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Pſal 91.6.</note>. If eight and thirty yeeres ſickneſſe will not admoniſh this man, then let him looke for a longer, or more loathſome diſeaſe. <hi>A worſe thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where it is worth our noting, that hee ſpeakes not of a poſitiue puniſhment, ſaying, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Malum, Euil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall happen vnto him,</hi> No, nor yet <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which <hi>Beza</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Beza annotat. in Mat. <hi>12.45.</hi>
               </note> ſaith is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>Aliquid deterius quám prius</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Syrus graec. in loc.</note>; A thing farre worſe then the former, ſome hopeleſſe, helpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, remedileſſe thing. All which leſſoneth vs thus much: <hi>That God will bring greater and heauier plagues on men when they will not profit by leſſer.</hi> The Scriptures are full theſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naced, and manifeſted, threatned and executed iudgements. <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Iſraell,</hi> the one <hi>Foes</hi> the other <hi>Friends,</hi> the one <hi>Slaues</hi> the other <hi>Seruants,</hi> the one <hi>Baſtards</hi> the other <hi>Sonnes,</hi> will make plaine the point in hand.</p>
            <p>If an Armie of <hi>Flies,</hi> of <hi>Frogges,</hi> and of <hi>Lice</hi> (euen Gods little finger) cannot make <hi>Pharaoh</hi> relent, nor <hi>Egypt</hi> repent<note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 8.6.16 19.24.</note>, behold how he layeth his <hi>Loynes</hi> on him and them, euen <hi>Greater plagues,</hi> as <hi>Moraine on beaſts, cap.</hi> 9.3. <hi>Scabbes brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out on Man and Beaſt. Verſe</hi> 10. <hi>Horrible thunder and lightning which ſmote Man and Beaſt, Herbe and Tree, Verſe</hi> 23.25. Yea, <hi>Graſhoppers</hi> in all <hi>quarters. cap.</hi> 10 13. <hi>Blacke darkeneſſe in the land of Egypt three dayes, Verſe</hi> 22. Nay which is yet worſt of all, <hi>All the firſt borne of Pharaoh, that ſate on the Throne, Vnto the firſt-borne of the Captiue that was in Priſon,</hi> (<hi>cap.</hi> 12.29) <hi>ſhall be ſmitten; yea drowned and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne in the midſt of the Sea. Cap.</hi> 14 26.27.28. So fiery is Gods wrath, ſo fierce is his diſpleaſure, that our ſinnes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing, ſhall increaſe his puniſhments, and make him full
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2990:22"/>of rage. Yea, and this will he doe, not onely to <hi>Egypt,</hi> but alſo to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> if it will not be mooued by little iudgements, by ſmall plagues to ſinne no more. Yea, if <hi>Iſraels ſlaughter of euery man his Brother, euery man his Neighbour, euery man his Companion, to the number of</hi> 3000<note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 32.27.28.</note>. if this wil not cauſe them <hi>To ſinne no more,</hi> why then beheld what God will doe: <hi>Hee will cauſe fire to conſume them, to the vtmoſt of their Hoaſt. Numb.</hi> 11.1. <hi>He will ſend an Exceeding great plague. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe</hi> 33. <hi>Fiery Serpents ſhall ſting them that they die. Numb.</hi> 21.6. <hi>They ſhall flie before the men of A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ioſhua</hi> 7 4. <hi>And they ſhall be ſold into the hands of the Philiſtims. Iudg.</hi> 10.7. <hi>Yea,</hi> and if theſe things will not make them to ceaſe ſinning, behold, how that God neither will ceaſe puniſhing, but <hi>Worſe things ſhall happen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euen the Fire of Gods Wrath ſhall be kindled, burning to the bottome of hell, conſuming the earth with it's increaſe, ſetting on fire the foundations of the Mountaines, ſpending plagues vpon them, beſtowing his Arrowes burring them with hunger<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming them with heate, and with bitter diſtruction</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 32.22.23.24.25.26.</note>. Nay yet <hi>Worſe</hi> things then theſe ſhall happen; <hi>Euen the ſpirit of ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, Eyes that they ſee not, and Eares that they heare not to this day</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Eſay 6.9.</note>. Oh fearefull and intollerable puniſhment, yet ſuch as God doth impoſe on vs for two maine reaſons.
<list>
                  <item>1 In regard of his owne honour.</item>
                  <item>2 In reſpect of our ſecuritie.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, if God ſhould not increaſe his puniſhments according to the encreaſing of our ſinnes, why the wicked would thinke that there were no God, or that that God had no power, or if he had power, yet that they could ouercome it with their ſtubbornneſſe; but take heede of this and know, <hi>Nullas tam atroces, &amp; ſaeuas eſſe paenas, quibus non aliquid addere poſſit Dominus</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Cal. in Text.</note>, That there are no puniſhments ſo great yet laide vpon the wicked, but that the Lord, <hi>Iehouah,</hi> is able to make yet much greater. Doe mortall Monarchs and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kings ſtand ſo much vpon their honour, as to gather mighty forces againſt a Rebell, whom they cannot ſubdue by a few: And ſhall the Immortall God, and King of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, giue ouer his armes vntill his rebels be brought in?
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2990:22"/>Surely no, for be we what we will be or can be in greatneſſe, yet <hi>If we walke ſtubbornely againſt him, then will he walke, ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornely againſt vs, and ſmite vs euen ſeauen times more for our ſinnes, &amp;c</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Leuit. 26.21. <hi>ad</hi> 29.30.</note>. So that all men may ſee and ſay too; <hi>That as Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily as there is a Reward for the righteous, ſo doubtleſſely there is a God that Iudgeth the earth</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 58.11.</note>. So that we ſhall not neede to aske that queſtion of olde: <hi>Where is that God of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Mal. 2.17.</note>? For hee ſhall come on vs ſuddenly, and ſmite vs ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely if we will yet <hi>Sinne more and more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But weigh the ſecond reaſon of this point; and that is,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Leſt men ſhould be too ſecure,</hi> who becauſe <hi>ſentence is deferred, and not executed ſpeedily, therefore mens hearts are fully ſet to doe euill</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Eccles. 8.11.</note>, Which God ſeeing, and patiently abiding for a while, doth at laſt rouze vp himſelfe like a <hi>Roaring Lyon,</hi> beſtirre himſelfe like an <hi>Angry Elephant,</hi> doth whet his ſword like a <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aliant Captaine,</hi> and ſharpeneth his Arrowes like a <hi>Bloody Archer,</hi> as if he would neuer ceaſe vntill hee had eaten his prey; as if he would neuer be ſtill till he had reuenged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the full; as if he would neuer giue ouer ſmiting his enemies vpon the Cheeke-bone, vntill his ſword had eaten their fleſh, and his Arrowes had beene drunke with their bloud. Loe thus doth the <hi>Lyon roare, and who will not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Amos 3.8.</note>? thus doth he puniſh fearefully where men doe liue ſenſually and ſinfully, and who then will not <hi>ſtand in Awe and ſinne not?</hi> But now let vs apply this point. <hi>Doth God im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe greater plagues where leſſer will not profit?</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Come hither then ye ſecure and careleſſe ſinners, who haue been tyed &amp; bound with the Chaines of your ſinnes, &amp; yet neuer felt the burthen of puniſhment; or if you haue, it hath been but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; <hi>A little plague, a little fire, a little froſt, a little drought, a little enundation.</hi> On take heed and feare leſt theſe former puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, proue fore-runners of further iudgements. Tis worth our noting, that when Chriſt fore-tolde thoſe many euils that ſhould come on Ieruſalem for their contempt of the Goſpel, and refuſing of grace offered vnto them, he addeth; <hi>The end is not yet: All theſe are but the beginning of Sorrowes</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 24.6.8.</note>. As if he had ſaid, <hi>They ſhalt be more in number, and greater in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2990:23"/>weight.</hi> If the Cutting off the <hi>Lappe</hi> of our garments will not warne vs, let vs take heede that he doth not ſtrip vs quite naked. <hi>Si nihil Ferulis proficiat erga nos Deus, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Caluin.</note>. If God cannot worke on vs with his <hi>Ferula,</hi> with his Palmer, with his ſmaller ſtrokes and eaſier ſmitings: by ſending <hi>Barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ground; Blaſtings of Corne; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſeaſonable Weather; ouer-flowing of Waters; and almoſt the death of our Renowned, Learned, Religious, Zealous, Peaceable and Godly King;</hi> If ſuch ſcourges I ſay, if ſuch ſcourges of his hand, which are euident markes of his wrath, and the very print of his foote-ſteppes, whereby we may trace him comming out againſt vs to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: what can we looke for, but a ſudden, a fearefull and ineuitable plague to fall on vs?</p>
            <p>It is well knowne (and would God it might be euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly remembred) that God did ſhake his rodde ouer vs not long ſince, by the <hi>Biſhop of Rome,</hi> whoſe <hi>Canonized Saints</hi> (more deuill then Saint-like) did threaten vs with a <hi>Terrible blow</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Gun-powder plot. ann. 1605.</note>.</p>
            <p>This was Gods <hi>Ferula to flicke vs,</hi> but for all this let vs not be ſo ſecure; for as <hi>Saint Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours wrath,</hi> which was <hi>aſſwaged</hi> towards the Citie of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> ſo I ſay of Gods wrath that now ſeemes to be aſſwaged towards our land: <hi>If we reforme not our Corruptions and ſinnes, though this cloude be ouer-paſt, wee ſhall ſee and ſuffer worſe things: for I haue euer beene more afraid of our owne ſecurity, then of the Emperours wrath</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Chryſoſt. hom. <hi>5.</hi> ad populum Antiochiae.</note>: And reaſon good, for that may be exterpated by force of armes, but this cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piated and appeaſed, but by true repentance for ſinne, and turning to God: Which let vs all ſpeedily performe, <hi>Leſt a worſe thing happen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Know we therefore, whoſoeuer we are that lie thus ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure in our ſinnes, know we for Certaine that theſe are but the Phyſitians <hi>Preſcripts,</hi> which if we will not accept of, wee muſt endure his <hi>Potions.</hi> If theſe <hi>Ingrediences</hi> which are milde and gentle, will not worke with vs, then muſt we looke for ſharper <hi>Corraſiues.</hi> If we will yet neglect his <hi>Word,</hi> bee we ſure to feele his <hi>Sword;</hi> If we yet will ſin againſt the <hi>Light</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:2990:23"/>of the Goſpell, let vs thanke our ſelues, if wee poſſeſſe the place of <hi>Darkeneſſe;</hi> If wee will not profit by <hi>Precedent Iudgements,</hi> we muſt aſſuredly expect <hi>Succeeding Puniſhments.</hi> For certainely <hi>Worſe things ſhall come vnto vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, <hi>Doth God impoſe Great plagues where Leſſe will not profit?</hi> Hence learne yee <hi>Demy gods,</hi> I meane you <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and men in Authority,</hi> to be followers of God as deare Children: Deale with ſinners as you haue God himſelfe for an example; when <hi>Lenitie</hi> will not make your people to relinquiſh their corruptions, ſee then what <hi>Seueritie</hi> will doe, after kinde ſtroakings, let there be ſtiffe ſtrikings. Sinne had neede not onely to be beaten, but alſo to be buffeted.</p>
            <p>It is long enough, if not too long that you haue withheld the drawing of the ſword of Iuſtice againſt ſuch notorious ſinners as haue raigned in your houſes, townes, and villages. Well and worthily did you indeede to binde thoſe <hi>Beare-like and beaſtly</hi> Drunkards and Sabboth-Breakers, to the good behauiour, who would out-face all goodneſſe and commit all euill (and that <hi>By Booke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>) I beſeech you now be not weary of well-doing, but as you haue begun, ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue. God is certainly yet much diſhonoured among vs, in this place, by our <hi>Cardings and Kittleings, by our Dancings and Daliances, by our ſeruants Idlenes, and Childrens Vanities,</hi> which they vſe on Gods holy day, and therefore I pray you in Chriſts ſtead, let your hands be againſt ſuch in a heauier manner then formerly they haue beene; there are penall ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and lawes by which me thinks you might a little more ſuppreſſe theſe crying ſinnes, and outragious ſinners that euen in this place raigne among vs.</p>
            <p>The Deuils Chappel is here (me thinkes) too neere Gods Church, I meane the Tap-houſe to the Temple. Whereby it falleth out ſometimes, that their noyſome peſtilence, or peſtilent noiſe doe either out-ſound vs, or elſe caſt ſome of vs into ſuch a ſounne, as that we either cannot tell, or at leaſt care not, what is preached, read, or prayed for. Lay too therefore, oh lay too your hands for correction of theſe things, and doubt not but that at the laſt you ſhall finde the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2990:24"/>ſame effect in mens mindes by your corrections, as <hi>God</hi> doth by <hi>His:</hi> Namely, <hi>That they ſhall open their eares</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Iob 33.16.</note>, and make them both <hi>Tractable and Teachable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As therefore you expect the auoydance of Puniſhment, auoyd you, diſcountenance you, diſcomfort you, by ſharpe corrections, ſuch friends, families, yea familiars and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, as will not breake off their ſinnefull courſe, for which God will ſend <hi>worſe things,</hi> if we thus wretchedly ſhall grow <hi>from worſe to worſe;</hi> but farre be it from vs my brethren ſo to doe, nay rather let vs grow better and better, ſeeing God hath ſo mercifully healed ſo many hurts, ſeeing he hath ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſo many running ſoares, ſeeing he hath deliuered vs from ſo many ineuitable dangers both of body and ſoule, what can we doe leſſe then glorifie him in body and in ſoule, ſinning no more ſo haynouſly, ſo heauily, ſo wickedly, ſo wretchedly for feare leſt <hi>worſe things happen vnto vs?</hi> From which ſinnes and puniſhments, the Lord deliuer vs all for his deare <hi>Sonne our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, Amen, Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2990:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
